<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true narrative and discovery of several very remarkable passages relating to the horrid popish plot as they fell within the knowledge of Mr. Miles Prance ...</title>
            <author>Prance, Miles, fl. 1678-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35372</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15265482</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15265482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1192:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true narrative and discovery of several very remarkable passages relating to the horrid popish plot as they fell within the knowledge of Mr. Miles Prance ...</title>
                  <author>Prance, Miles, fl. 1678-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin reprinted :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXIX [1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by authority."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. His depositions concerning the plot in general, and a particular design against the life of His Sacred Majesty -- II. The whole proceedings touching the murther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey, and the particular circumstances thereof -- III. A conspiracy to murther the Right Honourable the Earl of Shaftesbury -- IV. The traiterous intrigues and immoralities of divers popish priests.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Godfrey, Edmund Berry, --  Sir, 1621-1678.</term>
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE NARRATIVE AND DISCOVERY Of ſeveral very REMARKABLE PASSAGES Relating to the Horrid Popiſh Plot As they fell within the Knowledge of Mr. <hi>MILES PRANCE</hi> of <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> Goldſmith.</p>
            <p>VIZ.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. His Depoſitions concerning the <hi>Plot</hi> in General, and a Particular Deſign againſt the Life of His SACRED MAJESTY.</item>
               <item>II. The whole Proceedings touching the Murther of Sir <hi>EDM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY GODFREY,</hi> and the particular Circumſtances thereof.</item>
               <item>III. A Conſpiracy to murther the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. The Traiterous Intrigues and Immoralities of divers Popiſh Prieſts.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN,</hi> Reprinted M.C.LXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory TO ALL PROTESTANTS</head>
            <p>I Lookt upon the following <hi>Narrative</hi> as juſtly <hi>due</hi> to the World, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I reſpected my Self or <hi>You:</hi> for as I am bound to <hi>disburden</hi> my own Conſcience by a full and Impartial <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of what I know, relating to this horrid, deteſtable <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and to endeavour to render my Acknowledgments as <hi>publick</hi> as the <hi>Evils</hi> wherein I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve been involv'd; So I am under the Obligations of <hi>Charity</hi> to Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute All I can to your <hi>Iuformation</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> That both the preſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, and Poſterity may take right Meaſures of <hi>Popery,</hi> as a thing ſo <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> to Government and Humane Society in general, and ſo directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to all the <hi>Ennobling,</hi> Holy, Humble, Meek and Peaceable Deſigns of <hi>True <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>riſtianity,</hi> That the <hi>Better Roman-Catholick</hi> any perſon is, the <hi>worſe man</hi> becomes, and look how much more <hi>devout,</hi> ſo much the more <hi>dangerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as when the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> had once deprived <hi>Sampſon</hi> of his <hi>ſight,</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de him <hi>grinde in their Mill</hi> at their pleaſure; ſo when people <hi>ſhut</hi> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es, and give up themſelves to be led blindfold by the Noſe with a ſtrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uceit, That they are Embarked in a Church that cannot <hi>Err,</hi> (which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Corner-ſtone</hi> of the Romiſh Building, and the firſt Principle they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e; although in truth, by that <hi>Church</hi> is meant nothing more than the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſurping, Domineering <hi>Pope,</hi> and his Covetous, Juggling, Self-deſigning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y;) After, I ſay, they are brought into this ſlaviſh hoodwinkt condition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wonder, if they be led forwards by the ſame men, to the moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Practices, as well as falſe Opinions. For as the Underſtanding is directed, the man, if he have any thing of a zealous temper, or be firm to the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he profeſſes, will ſuitably Act, and comſequently may with eaſe be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to think he does God the beſt ſervice, when indeed he moſt violates all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aws of God, Nature and Man.</p>
            <p>This I may the more firmly avouch, becauſe I muſt acknowledge my ſelt
<pb facs="tcp:103323:3"/>to have been an unhappy Example of it, and therefore although theſe al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> minable Principles and Practices of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> are already excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laid open by a multitude of Learned men, (for <hi>She</hi> has beſtow'd too ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſad inſtances thereof on the World, and this Nation in particular,) Yet wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have to ſay, being matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> ſo <hi>lately</hi> done, and wherein I my ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo nearly concern'd, it may (though never ſo <hi>meanly</hi> delivered,) poſſibly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome be of uſe, more effectually to prevail with them.</p>
            <p>The matters herein diſcovered are of a various, but all of them of a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> black and villainous nature; ſome relate to the Plot in general, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you may perceive how far the deſign was ſpread, and how no ſmall numb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (to my knowledge) were privy thereunto, and certainly the poiſon m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be moſt virulent at the <hi>Root</hi> when ſo many little <hi>Twiggs</hi> were therewith in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. You will find here (beſides what hath been already diſcovered a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> proved by others) notice of a curſed hand that durſt reſolve to attempt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Sacred Life of our moſt Gracious Soveraign; a Prince, who beſides the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtamp of Heaven in his Character and Dignity, and the dread Life-gua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of Sacred Precepts, <hi>Not to touch the Lords Anointed,</hi> carries in His Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſuch charms of Sweetneſs, Goodneſs, Clemency and Indulgence, as mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſecure him from Violence even amongſt Heathens and Savages; but no Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Innocence is Armour of proof againſt a Popiſh Knife; no Virtue ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to guard any from the Aſſaſſinations of a throow-pac'd Jeſuited R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Catholick.</p>
            <p>And certainly the Murther of that Loyal Proteſtant-Magiſtrate, Sir <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mund-bury Godfrey,</hi> was a thing ſo helliſh in it ſelf, and yet through Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Over-ruling Providence, ſo very conſiderable in its influences to this poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nations preſervation, That I am confident it will be no mean ſatisfaction t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all good Proteſtants to be aſcertained of all (even the ſmalleſt) <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> relating thereunto; which as far as came within my knowledge, I have here freely and faithfully ſet forth, without adding a word beyond the Truth out of prejudice, or any ſiniſter end; or concealing any thing for my ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reputation; For though to <hi>commit Sin</hi> be the greateſt of <hi>ſhame,</hi> yet ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and penitently to <hi>confeſs</hi> it, to the Glory of God, and warning of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Neighbour, is no diſgrace, but the greateſt <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>beſt</hi> ſervice a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced Criminal can be capable of, or able to perform.</p>
            <p>Nor was their other Conſpiracy againſt the Life of that Noble Lord, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> herein likewife ſet forth, leſs wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and barbarous on their part in the <hi>deſign,</hi> though <hi>fruſtrated</hi> by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> of God, who I truſt will continually bring to nought all the miſchie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Counſels of theſe Romiſh <hi>Achitophels,</hi> and caſt the cruel Devices of ſuch Aſſaſſinates on their own heads.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103323:3"/>
As for that part which concerns the <hi>Ill Lives</hi> of ſeveral of their Prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e ſame is not inſerted out of any <hi>Spleen</hi> or Ill will to their Perſons, (for to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>veral of them in the Courſe of my <hi>Trade</hi> I have been beholden, as far as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were my Cuſtomers) but to give our <hi>Engliſh</hi> World a Taſte of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ces of the Leading men of that Apoſtate Church, and to perſwade, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>le, Lay-Romaniſts, to conſider what kind of Perſons they are, on whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eves they ſo blindly <hi>pin their Faith,</hi> and to whoſe Conduct they Truſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atter of ſuch unſpeakable Importance, as the Salvation or Eternal deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>on of their Souls: And this I the rather recommend, and hope may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>valent with <hi>others,</hi> becauſe it had ſome weight with my ſelf; for next to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ections on the odious <hi>Plot</hi> they were carrying on, and the vile <hi>murther</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y had engaged me in, The certain knowledge of the cloſe hypocriſie or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fs Prophaneſs and <hi>lewd Lives</hi> of their Ghoſtly Fathers (at leaſt moſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſe I had the unhappineſs to be intimately acquainted with, which were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a few, though I accuſe not All in that particular) had a ſtrong Influence awaken my thoughts to quit their Communion; As conceiving that muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a bad Cauſe which us'd ſuch wicked means to ſupport it, and that it was way likely <hi>That</hi> ſhould be the true Religion, which had no better Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e on the Converſations of thoſe who were its <hi>Prieſts</hi> and chief Promoters. The far greateſt part of this whole Narrative hath already been <hi>atteſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Oath:</hi> As for the reſt that is therein aſſerted, as on my own knowledge, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll at any time be ready to juſtifie and prove the ſame: And what I received information from others, is every where <hi>ſo</hi> expreſſed, with the Reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> circumſtances inducing the credit I gave thereunto. For as I was educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> amongſt them from my Childhood, ſo I had a great acquaintance and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>iliarity with many of the Fathers and moſt zealous perſons of that party <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ut the Town, having been ſeveral years her Majeſties Goldſmith, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>f of my Trade depending on Prieſts &amp; others of the <hi>Rom. Cath. perſwaſion.</hi> The reaſon why I preſume to dedicate this mean Narrative to ſo great a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y as all <hi>you worthy Proteſtants</hi> in general, ſeemeth to me juſt, becauſe <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>excuſable,</hi> becauſe in ſome ſort <hi>neceſſary;</hi> I make you as it were All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies to theſe Preſents, not only that there may be ſo many <hi>living witneſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nſt me,</hi> if ever either there ſhould be any wilful untruth found therein, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I ſhould fall back, (which God forbid) from that pure Religion which you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſs, and I moſt cordially though lately have embraced; but alſo more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y thereby to engage your <hi>united Prayers</hi> to God, as well for my <hi>perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and growth in Chriſtian knowledge, as for my <hi>preſervation</hi> againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce of thoſe reſtleſs enemies, from whom I am to expect the <hi>worſt</hi> that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>revenge</hi> can ſuggeſt, or <hi>cruel malice</hi> execute; partly for my relinquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:103323:4"/>of them, but much more for diſcloſing ſome of their Proceed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein already they have not been wanting, for beſides lies and ſlander <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> duſtriouſly ſpread, to vilifie and make me odious, and the depriving me (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as in them lies) of the means of a Livelihood, I was of late credibly infor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of a reſolved deſign againſt my life, and that three perſons had dogged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for ſome time for that purpoſe: <hi>But the Lord is my God, of whom then ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> afraid?</hi> To his infinite <hi>protection</hi> I reſign my ſelf, and next under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> from whoſe moſt <hi>Gracious Majeſty,</hi> as like who from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords of his moſt Honourable Council, as well as the Right Honourable the Houſe of Peers, I have upon all occaſions found all juſt encouragement and very great <hi>indulgence,</hi> which with a thankful heart I deſire to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> morate, and publiſh for the encouragement of others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (eſpecially the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who ſway the reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> their pleaſure) are a moſt vigilant and unwearied ſort of people to propag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> their falſe Doctrines, and ſpread their tyranny; I ſpeak it experimenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> who have had the advantage in a great meaſure to know them; no defeat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>daunt</hi> them, nor ſcarce any diſappointments <hi>diſcourage</hi> them: no ſooner is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Plot diſcovered, but they preſently lay another. For 'tis a Rule that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Prieſts injoyn their people to believe, I may I am confident ſay of moſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> firmly as their Creed, that their Religion ſhall infallibly one day or other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſtored and eſtabliſhed again in <hi>England;</hi> and being thus verily perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they bear up under all Miſcarriages, and ſtill vigorouſly purſue the <hi>main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſign,</hi> though in <hi>new methods,</hi> and with different Inſtruments. And therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will certainly concern Proteſtants to be as careful and active to prevent th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſigns, and preſerve their own Religion and Lives, as the other are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtroy both: you have now an opportunity put into your hands to cruſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Cockatrices egg: O may you all in your ſeveral places and ſtations impro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it with wiſdom, and with courage, and with integrity: For if the neck of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Deſign be not now throughly broken, if Popery be not now ham-ſtrung <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England;</hi> if the Serpents head be not bruiz'd, and the Vitals deſtroyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may juſtly be feared, that it will revive again, and then the Plot will be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> laid to ſleep, &amp; not prevented, &amp; the latter end prove worſe than the beginning.</p>
            <p>But who am I, to adviſe ſo great and ſo wiſe a Body? May the God of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom adviſe you and direct you, and protect you in his Truth and in his fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> And ſo begging all your Prayers on my behalf, I ſhall conclude, and ſubſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A Hearty Well-wiſher to the Proteſtant Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and the welfare of the King and People,</hi> MILES PRANCE</signed> 
               <dateline>Covent-Garden, <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 26 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:4"/>
            <head>A NARRATIVE OF The whole PROCEEDINGS touching the MURTHER OF Sir EDMONDBURY GODFREY; AND Several other Paſſages relating to the <hi>Horrid Popiſh Plot,</hi> Which came within the Knowledge of MILES PRAUNCE Of St. <hi>Giles's in the Fields,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> GOLDSMITH.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MIles Praunce</hi> was from his Infancy bred up in that Perſwaſion, which calls it ſelf the Roman Catholick Religion, having ſeveral very near Relations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged therein; and being under the ſtrong Prejudices of Education, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Incitements of the Prieſts, was very zealous for advancing that Church; being made believe, That in order to that end, no means ought to be avoided or eſteemed unlawful.</p>
            <p>He had, by long Converſation, contracted as large and intimate an Acquaintance both with the Prieſts and Jeſuits reſiding in <hi>England,</hi> (eſpecially about <hi>London</hi>) as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with Perſons of Quality of the Romiſh Profeſſion, as any man of his Circumſtance was capable of.</p>
            <p>He doth well know, that for divers years laſt paſt, it hath been a general Opinion and Expectation amongſt Papiſts, That their Religion ſhould in ſome ſhort time b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> publickly re-eſtabliſhed in <hi>England.</hi> And this vain Conceit their Prieſts did alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very induſteiouſly nouriſh in them, but with words more open and peremptory here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> late, than before: ſo that he, as well as others, had for ſeveral years, a general Intim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, That ſome great thing was ſhortly to be done for the Roman Catholick Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and that the Redemption (as they were wont to call it) was drawing nigh. But t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> firſt direct and particular Information he received of the Plot, or any formed Deſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and Reſolution to take Arms, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> near two years ago, on the occaſion, and in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103323:5"/>
One Mr. <hi>Towneley</hi> of <hi>Townley</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> a Gentleman of a very conſiderable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtate, coming up to <hi>London</hi> with his two Sons, in order to carry them over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Doway,</hi> there to be brought up: For that is the general practice of the Popiſh Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to ſend over their Children thither, being made believe, that we have no go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> method of Learning in our Engliſh Schools or Univerſities; but that the onely gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Maſters of Education in the World are the Jeſuits. By which means, not onely o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Nation is ſcandaliz'd, and the wealth thereof privately drain'd away, but alſo it com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to paſs, that the Children of ſo many Noble &amp; Conſiderable Families, being bred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from their tender years wholly under their Tuition, they have the better opporuniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to inſtil Traiterous and Diſloyal Principles into their minds, plant in them an endleſs b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tred againſt the Proteſtant Religion, &amp; in general, gain ſuch an Aſcendant over the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that as they were their Maſters and Tutors in their Youth, ſo they behave themſelve as their Governours all their lives afterwards: the Eſtates of many Popiſh Gentry b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as abſolutely at the Prieſts diſpoſe, as at their own: Theſe things he knows to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true, and of very pernicious Conſequence; and therefore hopes 'tis no unſeaſonab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> digreſſion to mention them.</p>
            <p>This Mr. <hi>Townley</hi> coming to Town on this occaſion, did likewiſe bring up with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his two Brothers to keep him Company, and took Lodgings at one <hi>Airies</hi> houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Drury-lane,</hi> where <hi>John Fenwick</hi> a notorious Jeſuit and Arch-traitor, now in cuſtod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then had his reſidence: where, after they had continued ſome ſhort time, the ſaid M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Townley</hi> and one of his Brothers, went over to <hi>Doway</hi> with the two Lads, and left t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> other here; who, in the abſence of his Brothers declared very often to Mr. <hi>Praun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Wives Brother, and to one <hi>Adamſon</hi> a Watch-maker, That when his Brothers can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> back from <hi>Flanders,</hi> they expected to receive Commiſſions from the Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> other Catholick Lords concern'd, for the raiſing of men to carry on the Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Cauſe. And this his Brother and the ſaid <hi>Adamſon</hi> ſeveral times told again to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Praun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> at <hi>Pedley's</hi> houſe in <hi>Vere-ſtreet,</hi> where was kept a frequent Club conſiſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> none but Papiſts.</p>
            <p>That during the time that the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shafisbury,</hi> the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wharten,</hi> and Lord <hi>Salisbury,</hi> were confined in the Tower, one Mr. <hi>Keighly,</hi> a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (repated) of good Eſtate, was pleas'd in diſcourſe to expreſs his joy and ſatis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ſuch their Confinement: For, ſaid he, <hi>Now is the time for the Promoting of O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tholick Religion</hi> (meaning Popery); <hi>and if his Royal Highneſs be but ſure, and will follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the buſineſſ cloſely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which he ſaid Catholicks had good grounds to hope he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and we can but ſtrike whilſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on is hot, and not l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe opportunities, I do not doubt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our Religion may ſheedily be ſettled in</hi> England: <hi>for no juncture of time can appear more f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or favourable for the Buſineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than the preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That about a year ago, being in Company with one <hi>Singleton</hi> a popiſh Prieſt, at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> houſe of one <hi>Hall</hi> a Cook in <hi>Ioy lane, London,</hi> the ſaid Prieſt, in the preſence of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Praunce</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Hall,</hi> did ſay theſe words following: <hi>That he hoped be ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſettled in a Pariſh-Church before a Twelve-month came about; for he did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t fear b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that the Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lick Religion would raign in</hi> England: <hi>and to advance it, be would not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> any more matter to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab Forty Parliament-men, then to eat his Dinner:</hi> he being then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing at Dinner with his Knife in his hand. Concerning this zealous Gentlemans pran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more hereafter.</p>
            <p>That one Mr. <hi>Ridiey</hi> a Chirargion, living at the Houſe that was late the Lord of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nor</hi>'s in <hi>Wild-treet,</hi> walking in <hi>Wild-Garden,</hi> declared, The he expected to be a Chir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103323:5"/>to the Catholick Army in <hi>England;</hi> and that he hoped the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> knew wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one chief perſon to command it, would much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and his friend in that concern. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſince the diſcovery of the Plot, upon Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi>'s information, there was a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Prieſt, one <hi>Fincham</hi> by name, being a Prieſt to the Lady <hi>Saveil,</hi> taken in the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ridleys</hi> Houſe, where he was ſheltered; but ſince, by the mediation of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ends; he is, as 'tis ſaid, ſent beyond the Seas.</p>
            <p>That in the month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1678. Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> having occaſion to write to a friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Countrey, but not knowing certainly how to ſend, went to one Mr. <hi>Paſton,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om he had ſome reaſons to believe could inform him therein; he lodged then at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Bamber</hi>'s a Taylor in <hi>Duke-ſtreet,</hi> and had great reſort of Jeſuits and Prieſts to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>amber: after he had ſatisfied him in the particular matter he came to him about, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty immediately fell into diſcourſe of publick Affairs, and the intereſt of Catholick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>igion; &amp; he bid Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> not to fear any thing, for all would ſuddenly be well: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the firſt place, he ſaid, <hi>It was true the King was a great Heretick, but the Lord</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aſis, <hi>the Lord</hi> Arundel, <hi>the Lord</hi> Powis, <hi>and Lord</hi> Peters, (theſe four Noblemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well remembers he named) <hi>would have a gallant Army for the depoſing, or diſpoſing</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e cannot now certainly ſay which of theſe words he uſed, but is ſure it was one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em) <hi>of the King, &amp; utter ſubverſion of all the Proteſtants; &amp; then the Catholick Religion ſhould eſtabliſht &amp; flouriſh in this Nation.</hi> And he then farther ſaid, <hi>that the Lords had already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en out Commiſſions to divers Gentlemen in the Country for raiſing their Troops;</hi> and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>med ſeveral of them; amongſt whom he well remembers one was Mr. <hi>Talbot</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ngſord;</hi> another, Sir <hi>Henry Bedingfield</hi> of <hi>Oxborough-hall</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and a third Mr. <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who lives within four or five miles of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames:</hi> others he mentioned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe names he does not ſo well retain.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That about eight or ten days before <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> 1678. he had a more clear diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the deſign in hand, That they intended to leavy War, to ſubvert the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for being at the Chamber of Father <hi>Ireland</hi> the Jeſuite, ſiuce executed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eaſon, he lodging then in <hi>Ruſſel ſtreet,</hi> where were likewiſe preſent <hi>John Fenwick</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Grove;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Ireland</hi> did declare, <hi>that there would VERY SHORTLY be Fifty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſand men in Arms.</hi> At which Mr. <hi>Praunee,</hi> as ſurprized, demanded of him where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey would have them, and what they were to do? to which he anſwered, <hi>We muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve them ſpeedily to ſettle our Religion here, or elſe all will be ruined.</hi> Then Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uired who ſhould command them? to which <hi>Fenwick</hi> undertook to make anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſaid, <hi>That they ſhould be commanded by the Lord</hi> Avundel, <hi>Lord</hi> Bellaſis, <hi>Lord</hi> Powis, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d others.</hi> Whereupon, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> apprehending the fatal miſchiefs and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of a Civil War, ſaid to them, <hi>What then ſhall we poor Tradeſmen do?</hi> the ſame <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wick</hi> replyed, <hi>You for your part of all men need not fear a Trade, for you</hi> (being a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ldſmith) <hi>will have enough in your way by Church-work</hi> And ſeveral ſuch diſcourſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en paſſed between them, whereby he plainly underſtood, that there was a grand Plot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d near to be put in execution, and that they were very confident of the ſucceſs.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That ſoon after this, the ſaid <hi>Grove</hi> came to <hi>Mr. Prannce</hi>'s ſhop to buy two S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r ſpoons for a Chriſtning where he was to be Godfather; &amp; taking occaſion to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their laſt recited diſcourſe at Father <hi>Ireland</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> askt him what Office he the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Grove</hi> was to have in the Catholick Army: but he declined to anſwer directly, &amp; at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103323:6"/>laſt ſaid, <hi>He did not know AS YET.</hi> Then being asked again, who were to govern t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> intended Army, he named the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> the Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord <hi>Peters;</hi> and ſaid, that they had already Commiſſions for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Prieſts themſelves were not only the grand Contrivers of this deſperate Deſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with Counſel and Encouragement, but likewiſe intended to be actually concern'd in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Butcheries, as well as the Laiety: for very near the ſame time, Mr. <hi>le Fevre</hi> a Prieſt, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was well acquainted with, as haveing ſold him ſeveral Chalices, Crewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Baſons, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>-boxes for Extreame Unction, and ſuch-like Utenſils, came to his Shop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> buy a ſecond hand Silver-bilt for a Sword; whereupon, he askt him what he ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> do therewith, for he had a good Sword already? the ſaid <hi>le Fevre</hi> anſwered, there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> times coming on, wherein Catholicks would have good occaſion for Weapons, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore he would be ſure to be provided, by getting another ſpecial Sword, and wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> have ſuch an Hilt to it.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Happening one day to ſee Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> that belongs to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> ridi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the ſtreets upon a very brave Horſe meeting him ſoon after in the Court at <hi>Somerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Houſe, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was ſaying what a gallant Beaſt he ſaw him mounted upon late<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whereupon, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Moor</hi> wiſhed that he had ten Thouſand of them; but ſaid, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he hoped in a very ſhort time we ſhould have Ten thouſand as good Horſes, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with brave men, well Arm'd and Accoutred, for the advancing of the Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cauſe: which he ſpoke openly, and in a braving manner, as if he were not afraid to ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the thing, nor cared who heard him.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In like manner, and much about the ſame time, he heard Mr. <hi>Meſſinger,</hi> Gentlema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Horſe to the Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> boaſt, That he doubted not but to ſee the Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Religion flouriſh ere long throughout <hi>England,</hi> and Hereticks to be rooted out: for he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ped to ſee a gallant Army one of theſe days, to effect ſo glorious a work. The ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>man was afterwards engaged in the horrid Deſigns of Murthering the Kings Sacre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Majeſty, and alſo of the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> of which a particul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Account is herein afterwards given.</p>
            <p>After God by a miracle of mercy to theſe Nations, had been pleaſed to give ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Plot, their inſolence was ſo little daunted, and their malice encreaſed; co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving new ways to deſtroy all that oppoſed them, and to involve us in Blood an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Confuſion. For,</p>
            <p n="12">12. When the Order came forth for tendring the Oaths of Allegiance and ſuprema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> one <hi>Mr. Laurence,</hi> an Apothecary in <hi>Drury lane,</hi> came to <hi>Mr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raunces</hi> Houſe, to borrow a Book which had in it the forms of the ſaid Oaths, ſeemin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry much diſſatisfied and offended about it; and after ſeveral Complaints, and mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urings againſt Authority, did ſpeak theſe words — <hi>I wiſh with all my heart, half the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment were poyſoned, for they will ruine us all,</hi> meaning all Papiſts. Now how exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerous may a perſon, continuing under ſuch deſperate Principles, and of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade, be to the Nation, in deſtroying privately, ſuch as ſhall oppoſe their Helliſh De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>? for 'tis reaſonably to be feared, that he that had mad zeal and malice enough t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſh half the members of that moſt Honourable Aſſembly poyſoned, will ſcarce ſtick to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a piece of his skill upon any particular Heretick or Hereticks, when the Intereſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ir Bloody Church ſhall command, or proſpect of conſiderable gain invite thereunto</p>
            <p n="13">13. That about a fortnight before St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s day laſt, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> having an intimate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>quaintance with the Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder</hi>'s Butler, he told Mr. <hi>Praunce.</hi> (but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103323:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th a great obligation of Secrefie,) That the before-mentioned Mr. <hi>Meſſinger</hi> (his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rds Gentleman of the Horſe) was to kill the King, and to have a vaſt Reward, if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aped with his Life, as 'twas well hoped, the buſineſs was ſo neatly contrived, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might: But however, if he ſhould miſcarry or ſuffer in or for the Attempt, then he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ving appointed before-hand what Friends ſhould have the ſaid Reward, it ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtributed faithfully to them by the ſaid Lord <hi>Arundel, Powis,</hi> and the reſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ords that were in the Plot. Whereupon, within a day or two after, <hi>Praunce</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the ſaid <hi>Meſſinger</hi> in <hi>Lincoins-Inn-Fields,</hi> after ſome previous and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tory diſcourſe, asked him, <hi>Why be would kill the King?</hi> At which queſtion he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared ſtrangely ſurprized and confounded, as wondering how he ſhould come to know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uch his traiterous Intention: But Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> ſeeming not willing to give him any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>caſion of fear, he, recollecting himſelf, ſaid, <hi>Who told you of it?</hi> To which the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſwered, That their Butler intimated ſo much to him, as a Friend; whereupon he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly ſaid, No, no, we are off of that thing now: giving him to underſtand as if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d taken ſome new Meaſures. Then <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> took leave of him, who ſeemed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uch troubled at the Diſcovery: and after he was gone a few paces from him, called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m back again, and asked him to drink with him; but he told him, that his buſineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>quired hafte, and ſo avoided going with him. Then he adjur'd him not to ſpeak of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at bufineſs to any body living. But afterwards the poor Butler came to <hi>Praunce</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>op, and told him. That he had received great Anger, and was like to be undone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe he had told him what Mr. <hi>Meſſinger</hi> was to have doue.</p>
            <p n="14">14. In the ſame ſtreet where Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> lives, <hi>viz. Princes-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere dwells one <hi>GROVE</hi> a Papiſt (Nephew to <hi>John Grove,</hi> lately executed for deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g to murther the King) who is ſtill, at the writing hereof, ſuffered to teach School <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere. This perſon, after the Condemnation of his Uncle, ſaid very confidently, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere was no ſuch Plot at all as was pretended, for it was one'y a Plot. of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ants: And to vilifie the Kings Evidence, though moſt plain and pregnant, (according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the uſual method of all Papiſts, who make it their grand buſineſs to throw upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em all imaginable Scandals) ſaid. That they were all Rogues that ſwore againſt his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ncle. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> (of whom he then had no miſtruſt, but lookt upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m as firm to their party) ſaid, But then what think you of the Fifty thouſand men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at were ſuddenly to be raiſed? which to my knowledge he knew of: for I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member he told me of it. Which plain Argument of his Uncles Treaſon from Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Grove</hi> not being able to deny, ſaid, <hi>That poſſibly his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle might ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at in jeſt.</hi> Such ſorry Evaſions will they make uſe of to out-face Truth, bolſter up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir villanous practices, and make ignorant and credulous people believe, That all their raitors are Saints, or at leaſt Martyrs.</p>
            <p>Further Particulars which have fallen within the ſaid <hi>Miles Fraunce</hi>'s Cognizance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uching the Plot in general, (though ſeveral material ones there are) we ſhall not here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ention, as being not yet fit to be publickly divulged; but proceed to the Murther of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey,</hi> in which Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was unhappily concerned.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:103323:7"/>
               <head>The Full Diſcovery of the Manner and Circumſtances of Sir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey's</hi> Murther.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Deſign of Murthering this Innocent and Never-to be-forgotten Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was laid, and ſome Attempts made to execute it before it was at all communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> for he hath ſince heard by <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelly</hi> (Iriſh Popiſh Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> concerned in the Murther) and others, that once, ſome ſmall time before they acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with it; a Gentleman paſſing by <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> that was very like Sir <hi>Edmon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> in Statute, Phyſiognomy and Habit; ſome of them miſtook and complement him as Sir <hi>Edmond-bury,</hi> but the Stranger denying the Name, or that he was any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſon, they were ſo confident, as to think he did it out of Caution to avoid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> And therefore peremptorily told him he was Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey,</hi> which he as po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively denying, they made ſome attempts to puſh him into the Houſe, but at laſt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving their miſtake, releaſed him, pretending it was only to have drank a Bottle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Wine with him. Likewiſe they ſaid that once or oftner, they dogged him into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fields, and out parts of the Town, but being in the day time, could meet with no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to diſpatch him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. On <hi>Sunday,</hi> wanting but a day of a fortnight before the Murther committed, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Queens Chappel, the ſaid <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelly</hi> together with <hi>Robert Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Cuſhion man to the Chappel, <hi>Laurence Hill,</hi> Doctor <hi>Goddin</hi>'s Man (which Doctor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Treaſurer of the Chappel) and Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> went (as commonly they did every Sunday to the Plough-Alehouſe by the <hi>Watergate</hi> (as they call it, that is the furthermoſt Gate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> paſſage going down out of the <hi>Strand</hi> to the Waterſide) of <hi>Sommerſet Houſe;</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> after ſome common friendly diſcourſe and talk of the Plot which was then begun to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſcovered. <hi>Girald</hi> the Prieſt, in a familiar plauſible way askt <hi>Praunce</hi> if he did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> know Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey,</hi> who told him he had heard of him, and ſeen him; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had no particular Acquaintance with him. Then he askt if he did not know wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bitter perſecutor he was to Catholicks, and a particular enemy to the Queens S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (which it is ſuppoſed he urged becauſe <hi>Praunce</hi> was one of them:) And now o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate (ſaid he) he has examined people againſt us, and got Depoſitions to fix odiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Crimes and Scandals upon us and our Religion; To which <hi>Praunce</hi> anſwered that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eard he had lately taken ſome Examinations concerning the Plot, but did not know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> particulars, though he underſtood there was a great deal of Noiſe abroad about i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd heard that Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi> and others laſt night were taken upon it. The other told him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hat the ſaid Sir <hi>Edmond-bury</hi> was ſo deſperate an Enemy, and had done ſuch things that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he were not taken off, the Catholicks would be generally ruined, and therefore it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſolately neceſſary for the Glory of God, and the good of the Church that it be done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd if we can find an opportunity to do it, we ſhall have a very good Reward from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worſe Man than the Lord <hi>Beliaſis,</hi> and therefore (ſaith the ſaid <hi>Girald</hi> to <hi>Praunce</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oking upon you as a good Catholick and that will not deny ſo good a Service to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Church; we would have you be aiding and aſſiſting to us in it. This was the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> effect, and as near as he can remember the Words of his firſt Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>To which, being ſurpriſed with horror at ſo unexpected and cruel a Motion, <hi>Praunce</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wered, no, he could not be concerned, nor would be guilty of any mans Blood for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld. For Marther was a grievous and moſt mortal ſin. The Prieſt replied, Alas, this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o ſin, but a work of Charity. There is no murther in this caſe, it is for the Glory of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103323:7"/>God and the good of the Church, and therefore you ought to do it. With ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er words to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n which wicked perſuaſions, <hi>Kelly</hi> the other Prieſt likewiſe joyned with him, affirming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame &amp; highly encouraging <hi>Praunce</hi> &amp; the reſt preſent (whom it ſeems they had En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ged before) thereunto, as a meritorious work. Yet ſtill <hi>Praunce</hi> told them he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Treacheroufly kill any man, for he was not able to forte his minde to ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tion; <hi>Girald</hi> ſaid, he deſired him to be no further concened than he would be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that he would make nothing of killing twenty Hereticks in ſuch a Caſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t there was no Danger in it, for it might eaſily be effected and no body the wiſer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>veral ſuch words and diſcourſes paſſed. At laſt they told him he ſhould not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to do the buſineſs, but ſhould only ſtand at a diſtance, and <hi>that</hi> they were ſure he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uld not deny to do, for, by their very declaring the Buſineſs, he was already as far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned as that came to, unleſs he would betray them; which if he did, he was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Damned, nor ſhould eſcapelong here without Revenge.</p>
               <p>Theſe, to the beſt of his memory were the ſubſtance of all their Arguments to him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r did they Aſſign any particular reaſon of their malice, only that Sir. <hi>Edmond-bury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>dfry</hi> was a buſy man, and was going about to ruine all the Catholicks in <hi>England,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d that it was neceſſary to deſtroy him, elſe they ſhould be all undone. In fine, ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tunate they were, that by theſe curſed perſuaſions proceeding from Prieſts whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>had been taught to Reverence, and receive their words as Oracles; <hi>Praunce</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vailed with, (with hearty Sorrow, Shame and Contrition, he defires to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it) to keep their bloody Councels, not daring both on a Religions and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> account to leveal the ſame, fearing as well Damnation in the next World, if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uld diſcover it, as Ruine in this, being one of her Majeſties Servants, and ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>art or rather his who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Livelyhood depending on her and other Catholicks. With <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om theſe revengful Prieſts by their Intereſt and ſome ſalſe informations might eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>do him, beſides the danger he lay under of a private Stab or the like michief from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</p>
               <p>Then they acquainted him that ſome others were engaged in the Buſineſs, beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe then preſent, naming <hi>Henry Berry</hi> Porter to the Queens Majeſty at the upper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urt Gate, one <hi>Lewſon</hi> a Prieſt, and <hi>Philip Vernatti,</hi> who did belong to the Lord <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aſis,</hi> her to fore Pay-maſter at <hi>Tangier,</hi> and much indebted to the ſaid Lord. Who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gether with <hi>Gerrard &amp; Kely</hi> (as 'tis believed) were the firſt that were ingaged in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ineſs, &amp; that the ſaid <hi>Vernatti</hi> might be induced thereto by ſome promiſe, that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bt ſhould be remitted, and further rewards promiſed.</p>
               <p>They I kewiſe ſaid there ſhould be one more in it, whoſe Nam (as they then told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he doth not remember. And as he ſince underſtands, there were ſeveral others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ned. So deſperately were the Original Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivers ſet upon this good Gentlemans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ther; That to effect it throughly they laid ſeveral diſtinct Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, and imployed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Seperate Agents unknown to each other. But thoſe above mentioned were all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t he then knew of for his part, or that they diſcovered to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> In the week following, ſome of them met with him ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the ſame houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d appointed to meet the next Sunday, which accordingly they did: Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ely from Prayers</hi> at the Chappel down to the Water<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſide, where they preſently fell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o Conſultation about the manner of effecting this Horr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rder. But did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to any Reſolation, but went from thence to the ſaid <hi>Plough</hi> to drink, where they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103323:8"/>concluded to dogg or watch Sr. <hi>Edmondbury</hi> the next week, and that whoever of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> could firſt ſee him in a Convenient place, ſhould give the reſt notice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Purſuant to this Reſolve, as he ſince underſtood, <hi>Green</hi> and ſome of the reſt were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sr. <hi>Edmondbury</hi>'s Houſe, and endeavoured to watch him, but as appears, could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> light on a fit Opportunity. They met ſometimes in the former part of that Week, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Praunce</hi> never concerned himſelf to go to his Houſe, or elſewhere, to look for, or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him; But on Saturday the <hi>12th.</hi> of <hi>October</hi> in the morning <hi>Girald, Green</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forth to obſerve his motions, and <hi>Kelly</hi> the other Prieſt who lodged in <hi>Sommerſet-H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and knew of their going, came about nine a Clook in the Forenoon to <hi>Praunce</hi>'s Hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to acquaint him therewith, and charge him to be at home in a readineſs, The firſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> went near Sr. <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s, and whilſt two ſtaid ſome little way off, <hi>Hill</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> up to his Houſe, and inquired for Sr. <hi>Edmundbury,</hi> and underſtanding he was with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Spake with him, and pretended ſome ſained Buſineſs as 'tis believed, but not certa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> known what it was, and ſo he returned to his Companions (This Account He relate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he had it from themſelves, <hi>viz. Girald</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> afterwards being not preſent then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf, but at home as aforeſaid.)</p>
               <p n="5">5. About ten or eleven a Clock Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> came forth all alone (as his man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was, for, being a plain Stout Gentleman, he never or very ſeldom went abroad attend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with any ſervant, which they very well knew.) They waiting for him privately, dogg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him to ſeveral places, up and down all the reſt of the day, as his buſineſs led him, till<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bout ſix or ſeven a Clock at Night he came to St. <hi>Clements,</hi> and went into a great ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> there, where it is thought he ſupped. Then <hi>Green</hi> left the other two, and came<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Prance</hi>'s ſhop, but he not beeing at home, but at a publique Houſe hard by, he ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, and informed him that they had now ſet Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> in St. <hi>Clements</hi> (but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> particular Houſe he did not name or declare to him, ſo as he might know whoſe it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but only told him that he muſt make all the haſt he could down to <hi>Sommerſet-Houſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Water-Gate, where he ſhould find <hi>Kelly</hi> the Prieſt and <hi>Berry</hi> the Porter, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Praunce</hi> left his Company, went thither, and found them walking in the Yard, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they three ſometimes walking, and ſometimes ſitting on the Bench, continued till ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nine of the Clock; And then Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> as it appears came fourth of the ſaid pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by St. <hi>Clements,</hi> and preſently <hi>Hill</hi> came running away before, up Street to give not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that he was coming. And ordered that for to wheadle him in, two ſhould pretend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be a Quarrelling, and having thus ſaid, the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> goes up again to the Wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gate, and ſtood there to expect his coming by, and intice him in. In the mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Kelly</hi> the Prieſt and <hi>Berry</hi> began a ſeeming Quarrel, but made no great Noiſe; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Edmondbury</hi> coming along the <hi>Strand,</hi> juſt as he was paſſing by the Water-Gate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (who well knew Sr. <hi>Edmunbury,</hi> and Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> him, as having traded with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a's) ſteps up to him as in a great deal of haſt, and ſays, for God ſake. Sr. <hi>Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfry</hi> be pleaſed to come in, for here are two men a Quarrelling, and I am afr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> there will be Blood ſhed between them. Pough, Pough, ſaid Sr. <hi>Edmondbury,</hi> refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at firſt to trouble himſelf, but <hi>Hill</hi> ſtill crying out he feared there might be a great d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Harm dore, and how glad he was to light on his Worſhip, who being a <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtrate,</hi> his preſence would preſently quiet them and therefore intreated him again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep in; The Gallant Gentlemans good Nature, was ſuch, not ſuſpecting any H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſigning to do an Act of Charity, and to endeavour that the Peace might be ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to his Office, that he was prevailed with by the Treacherous perſwaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Aſſaſſinate, to turn into the Trap they had laid for him.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103323:8"/>
                  <hi>Hill</hi> entred the Gate firſt: Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> follows him and immediately behind him <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ald</hi> and <hi>Green;</hi> they coming down as ſoon as they had paſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raunce</hi> (who ſtood cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to the wall unſeen) went forwards towards the water-gate, to obſerve any that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uld come that way, and <hi>Bury</hi> then went to ſecure the Stairs and paſſage by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>appel. But firſt he and <hi>Kelly</hi> were the pretended Quarrellers, and ſtood juſt at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Raile by the Queens Stables, and as Sr. <hi>Edmundbury</hi> went down, <hi>Green</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kt juſt behind him, having in readineſs a large twiſted Handkerchief, on a ſudden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew the ſame about his Neck, and immediately they all fower, <hi>viz. Girald, Kelly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>een</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> fell upon him, ſecured his Sword, pull'd him down, throtled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m, ſo that he he could neither Cry out, nor Speak, drew him behind the Rail and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve him many violent punches on the Breſt with their Knees, and having as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed diſpatcht him, and that he had lain ſtill for a while, fearing he was not yet quite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ad, <hi>Girald</hi> the Prieſt would have run his Sword through him, but the reſt would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t yield to that, for they ſaid then it ſhould be diſcovered by the Blood, ſo that at their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſwaſion he put up his Sword again, and did not do it; however to make ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orke, <hi>Green</hi> got upon him and punching him with all his Force on the Breſt with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Knee, wrung his Neck round; The firſt Attaque, <hi>viz. Green</hi>'s flinging the twiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Handkerchief about his Neck, and their falling upon him, <hi>Praunce</hi> ſaw, but then immediately went to the water-Gate, and as for the reſt of the Tranſactions, he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from all their mouths afterwards, and particularly as to the wringing of his Neck, <hi>Green</hi> told of it himſelf, for he boaſted of it; and the bloody minded Prieſt <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ald,</hi> ſeeing him Dead, ſaid theſe Words: <hi>Well if we could not have inticed him in here, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſolted I would have followed him down</hi> Hartſ-horn Lane <hi>that leads to his own Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd there would have run him through with my own Hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it was otherwiſe ordered by the Hand of God, who though he ſometimes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers wicked men to perpetrate their barbarous deſigns, yet he often over-rules them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o far as that they themſelves againſt their intentions, contribute to the diſcovery, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>prings by infinite wiſdom and power, Good out of Evil, and ſerves the intereſts of his Church and people even by the Cruelties of their implacable enemies. For had they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>killed him in another place, or diſpoſed of his Body in another manner, 'tis poſſible it had never been found out, and in that Caſe, or if they had not been ſuffered to be ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> infatuated by the Devil as to murther him; 'tis probable their Helliſh Plot had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficiently taken notice of, till ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the direfull Effects, ſo that Sr. <hi>Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> muſt juſtly be ſtiled, <hi>the King and Kingdoms Martyr,</hi> ſince his Death (though i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it ſelf moſt horrid and deplorable was yet through the infinite mercy of God, a mean to preſerve the Lives of many thouſands.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Having ſtaid at the Gate about a quarter of an hour, in all which time no bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> offered to come in that way, <hi>Prance</hi> went down to them, and likewiſe <hi>Berry</hi> came from his poſt at the Stairs, and then they all ſet upon removing the Body, which they carrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in at a Door right againſt the place where he was Murdered, and ſo up a pair <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stairs that goes into a long Entry leading into the upper Court by the Coach Houſe and then into Doctor <hi>Geddin</hi>'s Lodgings, who was Treaſurer of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Chappel to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Queen, where the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> lived, &amp; did all the Doctors Buſſineſs, being he firſt Doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> on the left Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in the ſaid Entry, <hi>Hill</hi> going before and opening the Door; Then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> carryed him up Five or ſix Stept, in to a little Room on the Right Hand, where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſet the Body with his Back leaning againſt a Bed and ſo leaving <hi>Hill</hi> there as being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103323:9"/>home the reſt departed, and diſperſed themſelves, every Man to his own Dwelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> getting home about ten of the Clock, or between ten and eleven.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Body lay in that Room, Saturday Night, Sunday all Day and Night, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> untill Munday at Night, and then <hi>Praunce</hi> coming from Home about ten of the Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> down to <hi>Hill</hi>'s, to know if they had diſpoſed thereof, or how they would do it, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe he had heard nothing from them; <hi>Hill</hi> told him, that he and the reſt had th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Evening a little before, carried him out to a Room croſs the upper Court of <hi>Some<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſet-Houſe,</hi> for fear Notice ſhould be taken of their keeping the other Room ſo lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> private, or that ſome body ſhould have occaſion to go into it, and diſcover him; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> went to the <hi>Plough Ale-Houſe,</hi> where he found <hi>Green, Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelly,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> preſently <hi>Hill</hi> came thither alſo, and <hi>Hill</hi> with a dark Lanthorn went with the oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> three, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To ſhew Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> where the Body lay, which was in the ſaid Room <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the upper Court upon the Ground, covered with a Cloth over the Head, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sword was not there, but ſtill kept hidden in <hi>Hill</hi>'s Houſe; So having ſeen the Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every Man went home.</p>
               <p n="9">9. There the Corps continued Munday-Night, and all Tueſday till about ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Clock at Night, and then all the ſaid five perſons, <hi>viz Girald, Kelly, Green, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> tooke him out of the ſaid Room, and brought him back croſs the Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ward to the aforeſaid long Entry by Doctor <hi>Goddin</hi>'s Door, but <hi>Hill</hi> going in befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his own Lodging, found (as they declared after.) ſome body there, ſo that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould not with ſafety lay him in the ſame Room where he was firſt before, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore they carried him into another Room on the left Hand going from the uppe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Court juſt oppoſite to Doctor <hi>Goddin</hi>'s Door, which as is ſuppoſed was Sr. <hi>John A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>undel</hi>'s Lodgings who is Maſter of the Horſe to the Queen.</p>
               <p n="10">10. There the Body lay Tueſday-Night, and till Wedneſday about nine a Cloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Night; and then all the ſaid five perſons undertook to convey it ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k again to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oom in <hi>Doctor Goddin</hi>'s Lodgings where <hi>Hill</hi> Lived, and where it was laid at firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey imagining as Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> ſuppoſes that they might have more freedom, and bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er opportunity to carry it from thence unperceived, than from the other place; Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uring the time they were ſo removing him, and juſt as they had the Body in the En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> accidentally came that way, and they not knowing who it might be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t the Body there, and began to fly, <hi>Berry</hi> running away quite to his Lodge, but Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> calling to them they knowing his Voice, came back and then they al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <hi>Berry</hi> who was ſo gone) ſet to their Hands &amp; got it up again into the ſaid little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oom in Doctor <hi>Goddin</hi>'s Lodgings, where it was at firſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. There they entred into a ſerious Conſutation, and the Two Prieſts <hi>Girald</hi> &amp; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>elly</hi> (whether by Order of Superiors or not, cannot here be ſet forth becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>med no body that had ſo ordered, but delivered it as their own Senſe) adviſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at the ſafeſt and beſt way was to carry him out into the Fields and lay him in ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſcure place, in ſuch a manner as that whenever he ſhould be found it might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed that he Murthered himſelf, which would much ſerve the intereſt of the Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en it ſhould be publickly known, that he who was ſo buſy in charging Catholick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th a Plor, was ſo troubled afterwards for ſo abuſing them in the ſame, that he made<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay himſelf; &amp; therefore it was agreed that none of his Mony or other things ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>medled with, the better to colour that Report; and indeed if they did take away
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103323:9"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y Note Book or other Writing form him, it was in <hi>Praunce</hi>'s abſence, for he never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w them ſearch his Pockets, nor doth know what became of his Band, but ſuppoſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſame might be loſt in ſome of their removes, and being found by ſome Papiſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en the Body was after diſcovered, and enquiry made after the Band, the ſame might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kept concealed, becauſed it ſhould not be any Evidence that he was murthered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ere.</p>
               <p n="12">12. This being well approved of, it was further reſolved to carry the body away that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght about twelve of the Clock, to which purpoſe <hi>Hill</hi> and another underook to get <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sedan, and appointed all to meet there at eleven a Clock, in the mean time they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent home. Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> calling as he paſſed, upon <hi>Berry</hi> to let him know that he muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ready on ſuch a ſign to open the Gate.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Near eleven a Clock that Night Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> returned and found all the four; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>Hill, Green, Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelly</hi> there, and a Sedan provided, ſtanding ready at Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or <hi>Goddin</hi>'s Door Now by that time they had contrived which way to carry him, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t him into the Sedan, it was near Twelve a Clock, then <hi>Girald</hi> &amp; <hi>Praunce</hi> going to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him found there wanted leathers &amp; were not able to carry him well with their Arme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hill</hi> provided Cords, which they tyed in the nature of Leathers, and then <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aunce</hi> took him up and carried him over the Court-Yard up to the Lodge and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve an Hum (which was the Token agreed on) and thereupon <hi>Bury</hi> came forth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ened the Gate and let them out, having on purpoſe to avoid any Notice being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, invited the Souldiers into his Houſe with Drink and Tobacco, for they ſaw no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>entinel at all, and at the Tryal, the Souldiers which that Night ſtood Centinel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that they ſaw a Sedan come in, but none go out, and indeed it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>le they ſhould, they not being there, but in <hi>Bury</hi>'s Houſe, where were Lights ſeen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d company heard talking.</p>
               <p>Being thus got out of <hi>Somerſet Houſe, Hill</hi> run before to get ready an Horſe. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe the Horſe was, or where provided, Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> doth not know. Then <hi>Girald</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Prance</hi> carried him into <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> to the end of <hi>James-ſtreet,</hi> and there ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n down; and then <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> who walkt by, took him up and carried him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g <hi>Kings-ſtreet</hi> to <hi>Newſtreet-end,</hi> and ſo up <hi>Roſe-ſtreet</hi> to <hi>Longacre</hi>-end. Then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t two took him up again, and carried him by the <hi>Gray hound</hi> Tavern to the <hi>Greeian</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urch, there <hi>Hill</hi> met them with an Horſe, and taking out the Body, ſet it on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe before <hi>Hill,</hi> and clapt the Sedan into an Houſe that was Building, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>niſht, leaving it there till they came back. The Body being ſo ſet on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k, <hi>Girald</hi> the Prieſt ſaid, <hi>I wiſh we had an hundred ſuch Rogues as ſecure as we have</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Then thoſe four, <hi>viz.Hill, Girald, Kelly</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> went away with him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leading the Horſe, and the other walking by on each ſide, whilſt <hi>Hill</hi> held him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before him, But Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> returned home, becauſe being an Houſe-keeper his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y might take no notice of his being out all Night, nor any body obſerve his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng home in the morning, for it was between One and Two before he got back.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Next day they met together, and then <hi>Girald</hi> told him that they had laid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dy in a Ditch belonging to a Field about <hi>Primroſe</hi>-Hill; and to make people think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enever he ſhall be found, That he killed himſelf, I, ſaid he, run his own Sword <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ough him, and left it in his Body, and laid his Scabbard and Gloves at a ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ance on the Bank.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103323:10"/>
15. On the Thurſday in the Afternoon the Body was found: That night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Praunce</hi> was at the <hi>Horſeſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>-Tavern in <hi>Drury</hi>-Lane, with <hi>Philip Vernatti,</hi> that ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> have been actually concerned in the Murther, but failed to be there; and alſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friend that accidentally was with them, knowing nothing in the leaſt of this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid buſineſs. There ſome people came in and ſaid, That Sir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſound murthered, whereupon the ſaid <hi>Vernatti</hi> calling Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> aſide to the Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid, Lord! is this mans body found already that was carried away but yeſternig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Thanks be to God that he was conveyed away without any notice, for now I hope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will never be diſcovered. He ſaid further, That he ſhould have been concerned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ſent to, but was not at home, but was ſorry he was not there, to have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtant to them. Then he askt the manner how the Murther was contrived; of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> gave him ſome ſhort account, but not all, becauſe his Friend being in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Room, they were afraid of talking long ſo privately, left he ſhould ſuſpect ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thing to their prejudice.</p>
               <p n="16">16. In little time after, the ſaid <hi>Vernatti</hi> met with <hi>Girald,</hi> who gave him an ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> account in writing of the whole proceedings and manner of the Murther, That he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he ſaid) might communicate and ſhew the ſame to the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> and other o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deſigners or promoters of the buſineſs, for their ſatisfaction; which Mr. <hi>Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> came to the knowledge of in manner following, <hi>viz.</hi> About a fortnight afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> met with the ſaid <hi>Vernatti</hi> again, who invited him to <hi>Bow</hi> to take a Dinner, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Friend of his: To which he conſented, and the day was appointed. But in the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were firſt to meet in <hi>London</hi> at the <hi>George,</hi> an Alehouſe right over againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Stocks</hi> Market; where going accordingly, he found Mr. <hi>Vernatti</hi> and the before m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Lewſon,</hi> a Prieſt that was privy to the Murther, and ſhould likewiſe have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at it, but happened to be abſent; theſe were got thither before, but Mr. <hi>Praun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had but a little time been come to them, before the ſaid <hi>Vernatti</hi> pluckt out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cket a paper in which was written down an account of the whole Murther, readi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame to <hi>Lewſon.</hi> Upon which Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> askt him who gave him all that ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Account? He anſwered, <hi>Girald</hi> gave it him to ſhew it to the Lord <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ellafis,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſt concerned.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Then away they went together all three to <hi>Bow</hi> to a Tavern; being the <hi>Qee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Head,</hi> one Mr. <hi>Caſhes</hi> Houſe, where they went up one pair of Stairs, and there Mr. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natti</hi> wrote <hi>a</hi> Note to one Mr. <hi>Dethwick</hi> who lived about a mile and an half o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> thinks, about <hi>Poplar</hi>) to come to him, and cauſes a meſſenger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be provided to carry it, who was a Cobler, whom he ſtrictly charged not to deliv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame to any but <hi>Dethwicks</hi> own hand, and if he were not at home, to bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> back again; whilſt he was gone, looking out at the Window, and hearing Fiſh cried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> bought ſome, and ordered the people of the Houſe to dreſs them. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> after ſome time, both <hi>Vernatti</hi> and <hi>Lewſon</hi> went down to deſire the Woman not to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them with Suet but with Butter, ſaying they would allow her ſo much the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for dreſſing, pretending fat would riſe in their Stomacks; but the true reaſon whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they declared above, was becauſe it was Friday (being as he remembers the Frid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> next after the Proclamation came forth, commanding Papiſts to depart the City. Thus nice and ſcrupulous were they in that paltry Obſervation who could ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> counſel, and without the leaſt remorſe, carry on a moſt Helliſh Plot, and premedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103323:10"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed Murther. Yet was not this Caution ſo neatly delivered but that the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an to have a ſuſpicion that they were <hi>Papiſts;</hi> for having a Barrel of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters brought, the Cobler returned with word, That Mr. <hi>Detbwick,</hi> would preſently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e there; who came accordingly, and was entertained by <hi>Vernatti</hi> with abundance of Complaiſance and Careſſes; ſo fell to their Oyſters, and preparing for Dinner: Mr. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natti</hi> was ſo eager to communicate the buſineſs, that he had got the before-mentioned Narrative of Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi>'s Death in his hand, and was reading the ſame to <hi>Deth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> who ſaid the ſame was very well; but a boy of the Houſe obſerving a paper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his hand, and having ſome ſuſpicion, becauſe he heard the name of Sir <hi>Edmund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfry</hi> mentioned (as he hath ſince made Oath) did liſten at the door, till Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> percieving ſomething ſtir behind the door, and being (as the Guilty always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re) full of ſuſpicions and jealouſies, ran to the door, and opening it, found him there, and threatned to kick him down ſtairs; and from that time they would not ſuffer the door any more to be ſhut, becauſe no body ſhould liſten. However there they continued all that day, and at night went every one to his home.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Soon after this, <hi>Vernatti</hi> was very importunate with Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> to go out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Town with him; whether it were to have done him a miſchief, as fearing to put confidence in him, and ſuſpecting he ſhould diſcover them, he knows not, but abſolutely refuſed to go with him. This <hi>Vernatti</hi> is a perſon that has been a great Traveller, and lived a long time at <hi>Rome,</hi> maintaining a Correſpondence both in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> with Jeſuits and other the moſt dangerous Popiſh Firebrands; he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently made it his buſineſs to carry away young Gentlemen to <hi>Rhemes, Doway,</hi> and other foreign Seminaries, and ſometimes young Ladies to Nunneries. In a word, he was amighty ſtickler in the Catholick cauſe; and a perſon ſo dangerous, that 'tis pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he has eſcaped the hand of Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Thus far this Execrable Murther was carried on in ſecret, and the parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned began to be out of all pain concerning it, not dreading any diſcovery; but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt the righteous God by an unexpected means was pleaſed to lay open the ſame, and in infinite mercy to bring Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> (whom the vile Prieſts perſwaſions as aforeſaid had drawn in to be an Accomplice, and hardened ſo far as not to have any due ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Guilt he had contracted) to be deeply affected with the horror of that crime heartily penitent for the ſame, and inſtrumental towards a full diſcovery. The bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing this to paſs was moſt aſſuredly the overruling hand of a ſpecial Providence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appears by the ſtrangeneſs of the circumſtances which contributed to his being fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> queſtioned for the ſame.</p>
               <p>For the better underſtanding whereof, we muſt acquaint the world with an Accident that happened before the Murther committed, which yet caſually occaſioned i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcovery ſo long after.</p>
               <p>Upon the firſt notice of the Plot and Commitment of <hi>Fenwick, Ireland,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſt of the Traitors that were firſt apprehended, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> being then blindly ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for Popery, happening to be in a Coffee-houſe where ſome people were ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid Priſoners, for the credit of the Catholick cauſe, did there ſpeak wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in their favour, which ſome of the Company thought <hi>ill,</hi> and gave (as he was tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome information againſt him; whereof having notice, to avoid trouble and charg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103323:11"/>he did abſent himſelf from his houſe the three nights next, and immediately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Michaelmas</hi> day, <hi>viz.</hi> on the Munday and Tueſday nights he lay at a Friends He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> right over againſt his Dwelling; and on Wedneſday-night at an Houſe by the <hi>Mews<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> But then underſtanding that the buſineſs was over, and no proſecution like to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made on it, he afterwards lay at home as before, and this was very near a Fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> before Sir <hi>Edmund-bury</hi> was murthered. Yet by occaſion of this, twelve weeks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was called in queſtion; for there hapning ſome miſunderſtanding between a Neighbour and him, who having got ſome intelligence that he once lay three Nig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> out of his Houſe, he will not ſay out of ill will, becauſe he acknowledges the hand of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in it, but upon a miſtake it was, that he did imagine that theſe might be the Nig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> whereon Sir <hi>Edmund. bury Godfry</hi> was murthered, and thoſe that ſucceeded it and u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> this naked ſurmiſe, bottom'd upon nothing that he or any that he could produce (tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Praunces</hi> Servants were ſcrutinized) knew of the matter, a Warrant was obtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from the moſt Honourable Council-Board to apprehend and examine <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that matter. Being taken upon that Warrant on the 21. of <hi>December</hi> laſt, being St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his day, he was firſt carried into the Lobby by the Houſe of Common where <hi>Mr. Bedlow,</hi> whom he did not know, having but once been ſeen by him before <hi>viz.</hi> between the Murther and carrying out of the Body of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godſon</hi> and at a time when <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> did not obſerve him, yet knew his face again, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> charged him poſitively with being concerned in that murther; and thereupon after Examination he was committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> on Saturday the one and twentieth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the Munday following he made a diſcovery upon Oath, and then did impeach the ſaid <hi>Fitz. Girald, Dominick Kelly, Robert Green, Henry Berry,</hi> and <hi>Laurence Hill;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe the two ſubtil Prieſts made ſhift to eſcape; <hi>Girald</hi> having not ſince been hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of, but <hi>Kelly</hi> was got into the Priſon of the <hi>Marſhalſeys</hi> by the name of <hi>Daniel Edmond</hi> being taken up ſomewhere in the County of <hi>Surrey</hi> where he retired to hide himſelf and ſent thither for being a Recuſant; and hearing of <hi>Praunces</hi> being apprehended made all the Intereſt he could to be gone, and ſo procured unknown Bail hired to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhillings a piece, and got away in <hi>December,</hi> before he was known to be <hi>Kelly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough ſince there hath been a full diſcovery thereof made publick; as for <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> they were forthwith taken at their own houſes, but <hi>Green</hi> was before clapt up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Priſoner in the Gatehouſe for refuſing to take the Oath, (for his Conſcience was wond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful tender in that, but able to digeſt a murther.) And when his Keeper came t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quaint him that there was another Buſineſs come againſt him, and that he was charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey,</hi> he haſtily askt, Who accuſed him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Keeper telling him, It was one <hi>Praunce:</hi> he preſently clapt his hand on his reaſt, and ſaid theſe words, <hi>Then am I a dead man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. On the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>December, Praunce</hi> was carried before the King and Council, here he gave a particular account of the Circumſtances of the Murther, as herein be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is ſet forth; and for more full ſatisfaction touching the ſeveral places he had had occaſion to mention, his Majeſty thought fit to appoint his Grace the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> the right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Oſſory,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uthwell</hi> Clerk of the Council, to go with him and take his Examination on the place, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſee if he could ſhew all the particular places be had mentioned to the Board; being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103323:11"/>come there he ſhew'd his Grace and thoſe Noble Lords, firſt the fatal ſpot, or place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> was murthered, the place where <hi>Berry</hi> was aſſigned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and where himſelf ſtood; then the door he was carried in at by the end of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es, the ſtairs, the long dark Entry, the door leading to Doctor <hi>Goddins</hi> Lodgings, little Chamber there were the Body was firſt laid; going to them all as readily as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> could do to any room in his own Houſe, which all appeared to be exactly ſituate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> had deſc. ibed them that morning before to the Board. But as to that Room where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>aw the body lie on the Monday-night, being croſs the upper Court, (though he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed them directly towards the place croſs the Court, &amp; told his Grace ſo far he was ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>as right, yet there being ſeveral Rooms, and he having never been there but once, that in the night, and only with a dark Lanthorn,) he was not able certainly to in the very Room. But as to all the other places he was poſitive, and ſo his Grace their Honours return'd very well ſaisfied in the reality of his Information.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Here is to be noted, That whilſt they were viewing Doctor <hi>Goddins</hi> Lodgings, <hi>Broadſtreet</hi> the Doctor's Houſe-keeper, coming to underſtand what it was for, and <hi>Hill</hi> their Servant was charged with the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a right <hi>Papiſt,</hi> to keep up the reputation of the party) voluntarily offered her Oath, did ſwear before the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> had taken an Houſe in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hope</hi>-ſtreet, and went thither to live and lodge at <hi>Michaelmas;</hi> whereas in truth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Trial of the ſaid <hi>Hill, &amp;c</hi> it was plainly made appear before her face, That the <hi>Hill</hi> did not go to reſide at ſuch his new houſe ſo ſoon, but continued his Lodging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> till about three Weeks after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> in which time all theſe Tranſactions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the murther, happened. She then further ſwore, that there was but one Key be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the outward doore of their Lodgings, and ſo it was impoſſible that <hi>Hill</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d go out and in, and all theſe things be done, and they within not ſee him, or take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of them; and yet before they went away from thence, <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> made it appear, ſhe was forc'd to confeſs, That there were four or five Keys amongſt them thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of which <hi>Hill</hi> did always uſe to carry about him, that he might at any time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in, &amp; go out at his pleaſure without troubling or diſturbing the reſt of the Family; Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> himſelf hath been ſeveral times let in by him there with, they in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rooms taking no notice, as he could perceive.</p>
               <p n="22">22. But now becauſe Mr, <hi>Prance</hi> would conceale nothing, but impartially ſet forth all happened in this matter, he muſt not omit the Relation of that Imbecillity (or what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ber and unbiaſt Judges ſhall pleaſe to call it) which has been ſo much talkt of, variouſly reported.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt true it is, though the ſenſe of the bloody crime that he had been concerne'd in, in ſpight of all the Popiſh Doctrines he had imbib'd) work ſuch Convictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> his awakned Conſcience, as to make this real Confeſſion; yet by the or thereof, the danger his life was in, the apparent hazard of being utterly undone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her with a certain reſpect which he ſtill bore towards that Religion he had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in, and other ſelfiſh Conſiderations he was once, for avoiding (as he then concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t theſe dangers, betray'd by humane frailty ſo far to retract by word of, mouth, what he before moſt truly conſeſſed upon oath, as to ſay before the King and Council, <hi>That he innocent, and they all</hi> (meaning the reſt accuſed) <hi>were innocent;</hi> and that was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of all he then and there declared in that kind: For which he humbly begs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of God, his Majeſty, that Honourable Board, and the world. And though he dare
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103323:12"/>not go a bout to excuſe the ſame wholly, yet there are ſeveral Circumſtances that my alleviated it, and render it inſignificant to invalidate what he had before truly forth. For,
<list>
                     <item>1. What he before declared concerning the murther in manner before herein ſet fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> was ſolemnly upon Oath; this ſuppoſed Retractation was ſuddenly done under conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and fear, and not upon Oath.</item>
                     <item>2. He was at that time under certain danger of his life if he perſiſted in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, for he had no pardon granted, nor any certainty of obtaining the ſame.</item>
                     <item>3. If he ſhould obtain his pardon, he conſidered, That yet his Life would be ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> danger from the revengeful and bloody Prieſts and Jeſuits.</item>
                     <item>4. His mind was ſorely troubled, as with all theſe dangers, ſo with this further appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, That if he ſhould eſcape with his life, yet by this diſcovery he ſhould loſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> livelihood, and in all humane probabillity both he and all his Family be utterly under for as he was the Queens Servant, and that his Trade and ſubſiſtence chiefly, or ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> wholly depended on Her Majeſties Cuſtom, (which was certain and conſiderable) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> that of other <hi>Reman</hi> Catholicks; ſo it was not to be doubted but the moſt crafty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> placible Prieſts would ſoon uſe means by falſe Repreſentations and ſcandal, to dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> him thereof if he proceeded in this detection.</item>
                     <item>5. He retained ſtill a certain reſpect to the Popiſh Religion in which he had ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> been educated; for he had not yet intirely got his ſoul out of that ſnare, and therein he did then conceive, being ſwayed by ſuch powerful Inducements, That he might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſay, He was innocent, and ſo they were All; which in Popiſh conſtruction is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> deny that they killed Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godſry,</hi> for that according to their Divinity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> what the ſaid Prieſts had ſolemnly declared, was no ſin or crime, and conſequently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> might all in ſuch their Catholick ſenſe ſtill be <hi>innocent;</hi> yet this he muſt acknowledge ſomewhat doubted, becauſe he had never been at Confeſſion, and received Abſolute ſince the Fact committed, which all the reſt (as ſome of themſelves had declar'd) had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> and ſo might more peremptorily perſiſt (as they did) in averring themſelves to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> nocent; and he does ingenuouſly declare, That had he received Abſolution, 'tis his he ſhould never, or not without extream difficulty have been brought to any acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Circumſtances, together with a great diſtemper of body contracted by the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of Confinement, want of Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> occaſion'd that ſudden revolt of his rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and duty under that perplexity of ſpirit; but as ſoon as he had done it, Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his face, and would no longer be laid aſleep with any deluſive Popiſh charms; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he began to recollect himſelf, the power of Truth diſperſed all theſe temptations of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> tereſt, fear and ſuperſtition. If it were true, that he might hazard his Life and loſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Trade, if he did perſiſt in the confeſſion of the Murther; it was as true, and he fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> by experience, that he ſhould never have peace of Conſcience if he denied it.</p>
               <p>And therefore he was no ſooner returned from the King and council to <hi>Newgate</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> coming in a Coach 'tis certain was not half an hour) but he moſt earneſtly requeſt Capt. <hi>Richardſou</hi> (who had been with him, and heard what he had ſaid that morning for Gods ſake to go back and aſſure the King and that Honourable Board from him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt Confeſſion which he had made on Oath was true in all circumſtances; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that whatſoever he had ſaid before them that morning to the contrary, was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>only by the conſternation, fear, and perplexity of mind he was under, which the Capt.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103323:12"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mediatly did, and had ſince declared the ſame upon Oath.</p>
               <p n="23">23. The next day he grew more ſich, in ſo much that his life was deſpaired of, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uing ſo for about a week; during this ſickneſs, the Reverend <hi>Dr, Loyd</hi> Dean of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> was charitably pleaſed to give him a Viſit, and beſtowed much pains with him at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, inſtructing him in the grounds and reaſons of the Proteſtant Religion; from whoſe pious admonitions and labours, by the Divine bleſſing, he reaped much benefit fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e comfort and ſetling of his perplexed Soul, and thinks it his duty, for the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> publickly to return him his hearty Thanks, Being wholly taken off from the Apoſtatize, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oody <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which he utterly renounces, and doth freely, cordially, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purely embrace the Proteſtant Religion, and therein particularly ſubmits himſelf to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurch of <hi>England,</hi> reſolving (by Gods Grace) therein to live and die.</p>
               <p n="24">24. After God had been pleaſed to reſtore in ſome meaſure his health, having give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeveral Inſtances of ſtedfaſtneſs to his firſt Confeſſion, by making ſome further Diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the mean time, he was again carried before the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Right Honouable the Lords of the Council, and there being largely re-examined ſpeated his former Diſcoveries, agreeing in all circumſtances; and then his Majeſty wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raciouſly pleaſed with his own Royal Lips to give him aſſurance of his Gracious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdon, and ſoon after the ſame was perfected in due Form of Law, under th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Seal of <hi>England.</hi> For which with deepeſt ſenſe of humility and gratitude, he de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red himſelf ever ready to pay moſt hearty thanks in all obſervance and duty, deſiring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> longer to enjoy that life which he holds by his Royal Favour, than he ſhall upon al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>caſions imploy it to the utmoſt of his Capacity in his Majeſties ſervice, for the ſafety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his ſacred life, the welfare of his Kingdoms, and the intereſt of the true Proteſtant religion.</p>
               <p>But whereas by Popiſh Adverſaries there have been ſeveral falſe and ſcandalous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports invented and ſpread abroad, that he was rackt or tortured in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh uſages forced to confeſs what he did touching the Treaſons and Murther afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, he does declare the ſame are wholly falſe, and that on the contrary he did the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eely within two days after he was brought in there, and that he received ſeveral Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vlities from Captain <hi>Richardſon</hi> during his Confinment under his Cuſtody.</p>
               <p>And he does proteſt in the preſence of God, the ſearcher of hearts, before whoſe juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dreadful Tribunal we muſt all appear, that as to the whole Diſcovery and Evidence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath given, he hath not therein been byaſs'd with any malice or ſiniſter ends, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne any wrong to any of the perſons accuſed; but ſhall conclude this impartial Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfreys</hi> Murther, with his moſt hearty prayers, <hi>That as be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th obtained the Kings Majeſty's Gracious pardon here on Earth, for his heinous Crime in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing ſo Acceſſary to the Death of that innocent worthy Gentleman, ſo on ſincere Repentance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d through the only Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, he may for the ſame receive forgiveneſs from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of Kings in the World to come.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:103323:13"/>
               <head>The Popiſh Conſpiracy to Murther the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and ſome other Contrivances after Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi>'s Death</head>
               <p>AFter the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> and ſome farther diſcovery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Plot, there was no perſon (next to his Sacred Majeſty) againſt whom the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of theſe Popiſh Conſpirators was more directly levelled, than at the Right Honoural the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> as knowing that till ſo able a Stateſman, and vigilant and acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Patriot, firm to the true Intereſt of his King and Country, and zealous for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, was taken out of the way, their curſed Machine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ions would be fruſtrated, and their wicked deſigns be rendred ineffectual. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they not only by their Emiſſaries and Abettors, both formerly and of late, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> endeavoured to aſperſe his Honour, but alſo entred into a formal Conſpiracy and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olution to murther him, and engaged ſeveral barbarous Villains to do it; tho a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Providence of Heaven over his Noble Perſon, and a timely diſcovery happily prevented.</p>
               <p n="1">1. About five weeks before <hi>William Staley.</hi> (lately executed for Treaſon) was app<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rehended, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was with one Mr. <hi>Meſſinger</hi> (Gentleman of the Horſe to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder,</hi> and formerly named in this Narrative for a Deſign to mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er his Sacred Majeſty) one <hi>Proſſer</hi> a Silver-ſmith, and one <hi>Matteſon</hi> a Barber then li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> all rank deſperate Papiſts, at Mr. <hi>Bradleys</hi> an Alehouſe in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here the ſaid Mr. <hi>Meſſinger</hi> grievouſly complained of the ſeverity of the Laws that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere againſt the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> expreſſing his apprehenſions that they would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e rigorouſly put in Execution againſt them, by ſome that were not lovers of their party, and particularly he named the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> as one of their moſt dangerous nemies, and who did moſt concern himſelf about them, and in diſcovering the Plot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d therefore he ſaid, There muſt be ſome effectual means uſed to rid him out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld, and declared that it was already reſolved on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That about a Fortnight, or near theresbouts, before the ſaid <hi>Staleys</hi> Apprehenſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was in Company with the ſaid <hi>Staley,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Matteſon,</hi> at the Croſs-Keys Tavern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er againſt Mr. <hi>Staleys</hi> Fathers Houſe, where in diſcourſe they were complaining of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e great Afflictions the Catholicks lay under, and what ſevere Uſage; they muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expect, if once this, Plot ſhould come to be believed, and be made out againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em; and thereupon the ſaid <hi>Matteſon</hi> ſaid, That if they did not take ſome ſpeedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſe to deſtroy ſome particular perſons that were their moſt active Enemies, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaning the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in general) ſhould be mined; and therefore in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> place (ſaid he) we reſolve to kill my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> (whom he then called, <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng-leader of the miſchief which they feared would fall upon them:</hi>) And further, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Matteſon</hi> ſaid, That he would engage three more to aſſiſt in that work of killing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid Earl, whoſe Names he then and there declared; that is to ſay, one <hi>Adamſon</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tch maker, and the ſaid <hi>Proſſer,</hi> and one <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> an Upholſterer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That ſome ſhort time after the ſaid <hi>Matteſon</hi> came to Mr. <hi>Prannees</hi> Shop, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ded a Piſtol out of his pocket, ſaying, <hi>This ſhall do</hi> Shaftsburys <hi>buſineſs;</hi> declaring had provided the ſame on purpoſe for killing the ſaid Earl.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That afterwards Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> met with the before-named <hi>Adamſon</hi> at Mr. <hi>Ped.</hi> at the White Poſts in <hi>Vere-ſtreet;</hi> where diſcourſing of News, <hi>Adamſon</hi> ſaid,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103323:13"/>That the Catholicks would be all undone, if they did not look about them, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y were reſolved to kill the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> Againſt whom, upon all occaſions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntion, both he and the other Perſons before nominated, expreſſed the utmoſt malic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hatred imaginable, as being, they ſaid, moſt likely to obſtruct and fruſtrate their reſigns: Likewiſe the ſaid <hi>Adamſon</hi> another time, not long after, did again expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h Deſign to murther the ſaid Lord, and then owned that he himſelf in particular was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aged therein, and would kill him as ſoon as he could get an opportunity: which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ords were by him uttered at the Sign of the Gridiron an Alchouſe in <hi>Holbourn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. About the ſame time the beforenamed <hi>Proſſer</hi> coming to <hi>Mr. Praunces</hi> Shop, did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ewiſe tell him, That he did reſolve to kill the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and aſſigned this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n or provocation which incited him thereunto, <hi>viz. For that he the ſaid Earl of</hi> Shaftsbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>and ſome other Proteſtant Lords, did intend to ruine the Lord</hi> Arundel <hi>of</hi> Warder, <hi>on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Plot, which Lord</hi> Arundel (as he ſaid) <hi>was his the ſaid</hi> Proſſer's <hi>very good Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmer and Benefactor.</hi> And alſo the ſaid <hi>Proſſer</hi> did, at Mr. <hi>Bradley's</hi> Houſe in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate, that he was to be an Enſign under the ſaid Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> in the Forces which were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have been raiſed by the Conſpirators, for the ſubverſion of the Government and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the before-named <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> about the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt or ſecond week of <hi>November,</hi> came to Mr. <hi>Praunce's</hi> Shop one day, and in diſcourſe did ſay That he would make no more to kill a Proteſtant than to Kill a Dog or a Cat, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pronounced with a great deal of vehemency &amp; earneſtneſs, &amp; ſaid moreover, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was reſolved to diſpatch ſome of thoſe buſie heretical Lords, but the firſt ſhould be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lord <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> and likewiſe the ſaid <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> pulled out a Piſtol and ſhewed the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaid Shop, declaring that he had prepared the ſame to do the ſaid Execution there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the ſaid <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> is a violent cruel Papiſt, of moſt dangerous principles, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be employed in ſuch aſſaſſinating bloody Attempts, appears by this Inſtance. That about three years ago being with ſome Company in a Shop in <hi>Dukes-ſtreet,</hi> diſcourſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſeeing a little Child paſſing by, he voluntarily ſaid, that he would make no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o kill that heretical Child than to kill a Dog.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That another time the before-named <hi>Proſſer,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Holbourn</hi> did declare, That the before-mentioned Mr. <hi>Meſſinger</hi> (Gentleman of the Horſe to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder</hi>) was the perſon that principally promoted the killing of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and that he himſelf was engaged therein, and did not doubt but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort time to get an opportunity to effect the ſame.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That Mr. <hi>Henry Nevil</hi> is very intimate with the before mentioned <hi>Proſſer,</hi> and hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for a long time been aiding and aſſiſting to him, and doth hold a Correſpondence with the Lords in the Tower, and with ſome perſons at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſending Letters duly thither<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and receiving great Pack quets back again from thence very frequently; and that one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Servants having ſeveral of the ſaid Letters in his Trunk, the ſaid <hi>Mr. Nevil</hi> about laſt cauſed the ſaid Trunk to be broak open (the Fellow being the in the Country) and took a way the ſaid Papers, to prevent any Diſcovery that might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> made thereby.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That Mr. <hi>Richard Nevil,</hi> Nephew to the ſaid <hi>Henry Nevil,</hi> did maintain a Corr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpendence with the Lords in the Tower in a very ſuſpicious manner, <hi>viz.</hi> Dreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Coach-mans Habit, he drove his own Coach, wherein rode his Coach man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103323:14"/>the Equipage of a Gentleman, and taking upon him the Name of Squire <hi>Duck;</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eing come to the Tower, this pretended Squire <hi>Duck</hi> commanded the diſguiſe Coach-man (who was his real maſter) to go into the Lords, and preſent his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>umble Service to them, and to tell them that he came as nigh them as he could, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ould be moſt glad to hear of their good healths; in which diſguiſe the ſaid <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent up to their Lordſhips Lodging, and ſtayed with them a conſiderable time, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e true Coach-man remained in the Coach. But ſoon afterwards the ſaid <hi>Duck</hi> was removed from that imploy of Coach-man and ſent away into the Country; for fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is moſt probable, that he ſhould diſcover this and other the like Actions of the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> two Gentlemen; this Relation came from the ſaid Coach-mans own mouth.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That in the month of <hi>October</hi> laſt <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> met with one Mr. <hi>Cozeen</hi> a <hi>French</hi> papiſt, and by Trade a Taylor, who walking together in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng of News; The ſaid <hi>Cozeen</hi> ſaid, that the King and Parliament deſigned to und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, (meaning the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) but, ſaid he, if I were to kill a man, I would kill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing as ſoon as any man, and if we had him in <hi>France</hi> we would have killed him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now; intending thereby, as he underſtood him, and as the Natural ſenſe of that expreſſion imports, to magnifie the Courage and Zeal of their <hi>French</hi> Papiſts, and now ready they would be to kill their King, if he were of another Religion, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> propoſed as an Example that he would have Engliſh <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks to imitate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> another time, not long after, the ſaid <hi>Cozeen</hi> ſpake the ſame words, or to the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e effect in <hi>Praunces</hi> Shop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A brief Detection of the Immoral Behaviour, Cruel Expreſſions, and Vile Practices of ſeveral other Popiſh Prieſts with whom M.P. hath been acquainted.</head>
               <p>HAving thus faithfully and impartially made a candid Diſcovery of the ſeveral Traiterous and Bloody Intrigues carried on by the Papiſts, herein before ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, we ſhall thereunto add a ſhort Account of the Manners of divers <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th whom <hi>Mr Praunce</hi> hath had Converſation; which he does proteſt to do, not out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any malice to their Perſons, but out of deteſtation to their dangerous Principles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d lewd Practiſes, and more eſpecially that others whom Education or crafty Infinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons have brought up in, or inveigled to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, may reflect and inſider what kind of people they are whom they blindly follow, and thereby be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>akened to forſake ſuch wicked and beaſtly Guides and no longer be led aſtray by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em, to the diſhonour of God, feandal of Chriſtian Religion which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etend to profeſs, diſturbance of Government, danger of their Neighbours, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard of their own Souls.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Amongſt many other Prieſts he had a particular acquaintance with one Mr. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tthews,</hi> that was Prieſt to the Lord <hi>Peters,</hi> who was a very bitter Enemy to all Proteſtants, and hath ſeveral times ſaid, <hi>That they</hi> (meaning the Proteſtants) <hi>were all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ainly and infallibly damned, and that it was impoſſible for a Soul of them to be ſaved;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther adding, <hi>that to kill any of them was no ſin, eſpecially if is were for the intereſt the Church;</hi> and the like wicked and cruel Expreſſions: He alſo in or about
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103323:14"/>the Month of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, ſaid, That his Lord and the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> with ſome other Catholick Lords, would ere long have a good Army on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and that all the Devils i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll could not prevent it, but the Catholick Religion would quickly be ſettled in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> We may believe him, that the Devils would not prevent or hinder i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſince it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much their Intereſt to have it eſtabliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, eſpecially by ſuch bloody and helliſh mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the conſpirators were reſolved to make uſe of for that purpoſe; but God has hither<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and we hope will ſtill, be grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſly pleaſed to prevent their Deſigns. This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was a great Dealer in Reliques and <hi>Agnus D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and hath cheated divers ignorant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vout people (as hath been credibly reported) of conſiderable ſums of Money for ſuch trumpery. He hath ofte times, with much reverence and ceremoney, as kiſſing them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhewed Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> ſeveral pieces of Bones, which he ſaid were the Bones of ſuch &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h He-and-She Saints whoſe names her had at his Tongues end, had attributed moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onderful Vertues to them; for he hath affirmed, That they being worn about one; could keep the Devil from one, ſo that not only he ſhould have no power to hurt ones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſon, but not ſo much as to tempt thoſe to ſin that carryed them about them: That in Tempeſt they would preſerve one from drowning, and if at Houſe were on fire if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in one of them the ſame would preſently ſtop the fire <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But as to the laſt it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that he and his brethren, the Popiſh Prieſts and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> are far more dexterous Artiſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> contriving devices to burn down Houſes than to quench them when on Fire.</p>
               <p n="2">2. there was occaſion before to mention one <hi>Singleton</hi> a Prieſt, that declared, <hi>He would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> no more to ſtab</hi> 40 <hi>Parliament men, than to eat his Dinner,</hi> beſides his Quality of Prieſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was alſo a kind of Sollicitor or Broker amongſt the Paciſts, making it his buſineſs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Peoples money into his hands, and put it out to Uſe; in which trade he plaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Extortioner moſt egregiouſly, for all that he could get above the due Intereſt of 6 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cent.</hi> being to be put in his own Pocket, he would not let 40 or 50 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> out for ſix months, but he would have 40. <hi>ſ.</hi> for procuration, which muſt be deducted on the firſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the Money, and yet the full legal intereſt to run on; and beſides he always would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up the Bond himſelf, and for that buſineſs, (for which no Scrivener ever asked above <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>) he would make the poor people pay five Shillings: Theſe Practices of his <hi>Mr. Prance</hi> can affirm on his own knowledg; and there are divers who have de. It with him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe terms who can teſtifie the ſame; and yet this Ghoſtly Father was a great preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> againſt Covetouſneſs and Uſury, but it ſeems he meant only in others, not himſelf: Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Caſes likewiſe he allowed himſelf the like Priviledges, for he would frequently Drunk, and ſtay out till one or two of the Clock in the Morning, or after, and yet go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame Forenoon to ſay Maſs, and conſequently received the Sacrament, which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch the People muſt in no wiſe be done, unleſs the party be ſtrictly faſting.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Byfleet</hi> and Doctor <hi>Guilding,</hi> two Prieſts, have ſeverally declared in Mr. <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cookes Houſe, and divers other places, That they reſpectively had turned ſeveral people from the Proteſtant Religion, and reconciled them to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ty of <hi>London,</hi> and that they hoped they ſhould turn many more. They were both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of a very vitious Converſation, but ſtily carried it. <hi>Byfleet</hi> was a mighty magnifier o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vortues and Neceſſity of Faſting to other People in <hi>Lent Ember-days, &amp;c.</hi> but as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf, could frequently, as is well known, diſpenſe with ſix penny-worth of Victuals <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d a quart or two of Ale, all alone for a Breakfaſt or Supper on the ſame days in his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103323:15"/>Chamber. As for Doctor <hi>Guilding,</hi> he was his couſir, and (they ſaid) had read Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſophy many years at <hi>Doway,</hi> but very much forgot his Ethicks in <hi>England,</hi> being ſo only addicted to lewd Women, that one could not but conclude he received his Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation from Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> or ſome of her fulſome Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>Theſe two la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> amed, and <hi>Singleten,</hi> were moſt frequently at Mr. <hi>Hall</hi> the Coo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> houſe in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y Lane,</hi> and there they dined, and Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> does verily believe, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>any <hi>Popiſh</hi> Books being above a Cart-load and an half, with the <hi>Prieſts</hi> Veſtment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eads, Images, and other ſuperſtitious Trumpery, which were lately found there it Sear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his Houſe, did belong to them; And the ſaid <hi>Hall</hi> (as he likewiſe believes) d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> now where they are, or were ſince they abſconded themſelves, for which ſuſpicion the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e theſe two grounds. Firſt, Becauſe whenever about <hi>November</hi> or <hi>December</hi> laſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ame to ſpeak with <hi>Singleton</hi> or either of the others, he the ſaid <hi>Hell</hi> undertook to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is buſineſs, and muſt needs deliver it to <hi>Singleton;</hi> becauſe when he called again he fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ot to give M.P. an Account of it from him; Secondly, Becauſe Mr. <hi>Hadden</hi> Servant Doctor <hi>Parrot,</hi> the Superior of Seoular <hi>Prieſts</hi> told him, that alwayes when he came w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>oney to be diſtributed for Maſſes for the Dead, <hi>Hall</hi> took the money that was deſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Singleton,</hi> and convey'd it to him. The meaning of which is thus, when any Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Catholick</hi> dies, 'tis probable there is a Prieſt (ſometimes two or three) by him, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er fail to put him in mind, and frighten him with the pains of Purgatory, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irtues of Maſſes ſaid to eaſe and deliver them from the ſame ſo much the ſooner, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eing therewith terrified, If he be a perſon of any conſiderable Quality or Eſtate, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ome happens but he leaves ſo much money to pray his Soul out of Purgatory, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oney is paid in to the Superior, who thereupon according to the Sum, ſends to ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſts ſo many ſhillings a piece, for which they are each to ſay ſo many Maſſes for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceaſed; the common price of Mumbling over a Maſs being accounted 12 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is Doctor <hi>Parrot,</hi> who is, or lately was the Head of all this ſort of <hi>Prieſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> credibly informed, That he hath been ſeen in Bed with a Whore, by the ſaid <hi>Mr. Ladden</hi> his Servant who told the ſame to Mr. <hi>Praunce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But as whoring is counted but a Venial Sin by <hi>Papiſts</hi> in general; ſo amongſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arce any are more devoted thereunto than their Ghoſtly Fathers, who rail ſo loud at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Proteſtant Clergie</hi> for having honeſt Wives of their own. About 3 years ago one <hi>Kelly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>iſh</hi> Prieſt, (a Kinſman to the before named <hi>Dominick Kelly,</hi> concern'd in the murther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Edmund-bury-Godfrey</hi>) being juſt Arrived from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Flanders,</hi> was brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dge at Mr. <hi>Praunces</hi> houſe, &amp; the very firſt night, the maid going up with him to war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bed, he began to uſe ſome Incivilities, which the modeſtly oppoſing, he proceeded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> violence, and would have Raviſht her, inſomuch that ſhe cryed out, and Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ife haſtning up Stairs, and perceiving his rudeneſs, being affrighted run down againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aring he would have done her ſome miſchief, and called in ſome Neighbours, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mediately coming in, cauſed him to deſiſt: for which M.P. Wife would preſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y: turned him out of doors, but it being late in the Night, and he wholly a Strarg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Town; He would not (though he were a Rogue) be ſo inhoſpitable to him; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffered him to ſtay till morning; However they were obliged to burn Candle all night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fear in Revenge he ſhould do them a Miſchief.</p>
               <p n="5">5. One <hi>Dowdal</hi> being Colonel <hi>Talbot's</hi> Prieſt at <hi>Twitnam.</hi> ſome few years ago, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103323:15"/>that Quality much Entruſted, ſtole and run a way with the Chalice, Crewet, Baſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h Copes, Veſtiments, Surplices and other Sacred Gear, provided for him to officiate Maſs with, and being wholly a Stranger, expoſed the Baſon and Crewet to Sale at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Prance's</hi> Shop, who fairly and at a valuable price bought the ſam, The Prieſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received his mony, invited him into a Tavern, and afterwards agreed, That he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come next day to his Lodging in <hi>White-Fryers,</hi> and ſee the Veſtments, Linnen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other things; which he did and offered him 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> but he would not take under 12 or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> However he would go again to drink, and at laſt walkt with <hi>Mr. P.</hi> home, who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g him in a parlour, where there was a little Girl of about 6 years of Age, whileſt he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to attend ſome cuſtomers in the ſhop, this Goaliſh Prieſt began to play the Villian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Child, and would have ſpoil'd her, (had ſhe not cry'd out) with his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Rudeneſs, which made him run into ſee what was the matter and occaſioned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to haſten away, and preſently ſhifted his Lodging, for going next day to look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him he was gone, out of fear (as is ſuppoſed) of being apprehended for the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of which yet there was no great danger; For though within a day or two Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> heard of the Robbery, by one that was a ſervant to the Colonel, yet ſuch was the Colonel's extreme Zeal, and ſo prevalent above the Reſentment of his loſs, that (as was by that ſervant aſſured) as ſoon as he diſcovered what their Prieſt had done, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all his people together, and did ſolemnly charge them not to ſpeak thereof to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſon, becauſe if known, it would be a ſoul ſcandal to their Religion; Adding if he found any of them ſhould utter a word of it he would run them through, A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of ſecreſy, (when ones life lies at Stake) almoſt as firm as that of confeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bout 4 years ago there was one Mr. <hi>Thomas Shepherd</hi> a perſon related to Mr. <hi>Prance,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being ſick, ſent to him to procure a Romiſh Prieſt to come to him, Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wondered at his deſire, as having always accounted him a Proteſtant, however it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Requeſt, and underſtanding he was very ill, and not likely to live, he did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>our to get one. And thereupon repaired to Dr. <hi>Hanſon</hi> a Carmelite, at <hi>Wild-Houſe</hi> of their Superiours, who directed him to Dr. <hi>Clement Mutus,</hi> a Benedictin Monk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nging to the Spaniſh Ambaſſador; but lodging then at one <hi>Irelands</hi> a Tobacconiſt in ſtreet, having told him the ſtory, and what a work of Charity it would be to ſave a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he readily condeſcended to go, and did give the man what advice he thought fit But the ſick party being very poor did not give him any money, which as appears he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cted; for next day the man growing ſtill weaker, ſent to deſire the ſame Prieſt again, which purpoſe Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> went to requeſt his company. But here truly found the old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erb verified. <hi>No penny no Pater-Niſter</hi> for this charitable Father told him no, he would for he gave him nothing yeſterday. <hi>Mr. Prance</hi> urged that ſo good a work as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a dying Heretick to the Church would reward it ſelf, and be meritorius. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>repl'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oved a Reward in hand, for all that of the other world; <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they get Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y us, and why ſhould not we get money by them:</hi> The other inſiſted, that the man was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poor, and had it not, and that he hoped he would not ſuffer his Soul to be leſt; his Soul, quoth he, do as it will, I am reſolved not to go to any twice that do not me; And ſo by no intreaties could be induced to ſtir; but the poor man ſoon after</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> So ſordidly covetous are theſe people, and not withſtanding all their pretences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng really ſo little Regard to the Salvation of men, that they would ſuffer a Soul
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103323:16"/>to periſh Eternally) as they ſay all do that die out of their Church's Communion leſs they can get money, by ſaying it, if indeed (as they impudently pretend) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their power:</p>
               <p>There is another Prieſt that did likewiſe pretend to belong to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſſadour, his name is <hi>Collins,</hi> who 'its ſaid is now in Cuſtody, when <hi>His</hi> Maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Proclamation came out ſome years ago, commanding away all Prieſts (but as were allowed) And that none of His Subjects ſhould go to hear Maſs, this lous Father got up on the Leads of <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> and there held Conventicle, and ſaid Maſs, having a great Concourſe of People that followed yet this pretious Saint, when a young Wench has come to him to Confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath been ſeen to get her between his Leggs, and ſo cloſely hugg, and kiſs her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> times over, as if it had been part of her Penance to be moſt filthily ſmuggled, was a common frequenter of Bawdy-Houſes, and has been obſerved many times to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> drunk out of ſuch lewd places, in ſuch filthy poſtures as 'tis a ſhame here to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>There is alſo one <hi>Davenport</hi> a Fryer, but of what Order, Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> does not member, who calls himſelf, and is uſually ſtyled, Captain <hi>Davenport.</hi> He is a kind ſtrowling, wandering Prieſt, that rides up and down the Countrys, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>Norfolk, Suffolk, Cambridg-ſhire,</hi> Iſle of <hi>Ely, &amp;c.</hi> where he does abunda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of michief in ſeducing people both from the Proteſtant Religion, and their A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to their Soveraign: For he makes it his whole buſineſs to infinuate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> News, unſettle weak heads, abuſe the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and its Miniſters, and ſerters, magnifying the Holineſs, Piety, Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by ſuch his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perverting the minds of many; For he has long followed this michievous practic never conſtant in any place, but always in motion from one Gentleman's houſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſome times amongſt people of mean condition, to ſpread his poyſon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; As if he deſign'd to infect the whole Country. He is no doubt a very danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fellow, and no longer ago then the laſt Summer was Twelve-month, there being Chapter (as they call it, that is, a General Convention) of Fryars held in <hi>Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſet-Houſe,</hi> whither many reſorted both from beyond the Sear, and all parts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Realm; On what Deſign (whether to carry on the Great Work) Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not, But hath ſome reaſon to ſuſpect it was for no good purpoſe: For ſeeing ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Twenty of them together, amongſt the reſt there was this Captain <hi>Davenport,</hi> whom then heard ſay, <hi>That he hoped to be a Captain once again in the Catholick Cauſe, fore he dyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one <hi>Bully,</hi> a Secular Prieſt, who formerly did belong to a French Embaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dour, but of late his Trade has been to run about Hackneying forth of Maſſes for tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> pence a piece at private Houſes, where ever he can get Cuſtomers. He was might ſtrict in his teaching (as they all do) That people muſt by no means eat or drink a drop the morning on which they intend to Receive the Euchariſt, before they come to Maſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe they muſt receive ſtrickly Faſting; Yet hath not only been frequently ſeen in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Road to Mr. <hi>Paſton</hi>'s in <hi>Duke-ſtreet,</hi> call in at an Ale houſe, and take his pot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more of Ale, and ſo away to Maſs; (Now a Prieſt cannot ſay Maſs, but he himſelf muſt needs receive.) But alſo he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been known at play at Cards, Tippling in Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any, and Drunk after One a Clock in the morning at <hi>Pedley</hi>'s at the <hi>White Poſts,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame day Trudge to Maſs and earn a Shiling to furniſh a freſh debauch. But the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103323:16"/>are not all the rare Qualities he has, For he is a notable Whore-monger too; Nay if the General Report be true that is currant amongſt Catholicks) keeps another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n's Wife; which Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> is the rather inclined to believe, becauſe he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> met them hand in hand in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> and other places.</p>
               <p>There is one <hi>Holt</hi> a Secular Prieſt, that uſed to officiate at the Lady <hi>Somerſets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>incolns-Iun-Fields,</hi> who is a virulent Enemy to all Proteſtants, and hath often be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard by Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> to declare, That it is impoſſible any of them ſhould ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ved. Now how ready a way is this to inflame Papiſts againſt them, and how apt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey be to cut their throats, and any way deſtroy thoſe whom they are already made to believe are Enemies of God, and nothing but fit fewel for Hell. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his was his Deſign, is moſt probable both by the violent eagerneſs of ſuch his Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, As alſo becauſe Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> hath often heard him ſay. That he did not doubt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſee Hereſſe rooted out, and the Catholick Religion e're long eſtal liſhed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Father <hi>James</hi> an eminent Friar at <hi>Somerſet-Houſe</hi> lately deceaſed, was for ſeveral yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſeſſor to Mr. <hi>Praunce,</hi> ſo that he had with him an intimate Familiarity; About year and an half ago diſcourſing with him, He told him, That there would ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be on foot a conſiderable Force to ſettle the <hi>Roman</hi> Gatholick Religion in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And that he did not queſtion but to ſee it eſtabliſhed very ſhortly. Upon which <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> ſaid to him, That he was confident that could never be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> without oppoſing his Majeſties Authority; and it would be a great ſhame and ſcand to <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, who had valued themſelves ſo much upon their Loyalty in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate Times, if they now ſhould be Guilty of Rebellion againſt their King. Whereupon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> replied, That in the Cauſe of God there was no Conſideration to be had of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nces; That it was no ſin to be active to ſuppreſs Hereſie, and eſtabliſh the Cath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olick Doctrine: For though Obedience was a duty in other Circumſtances, yet in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Caſe the Obedience to the Church was to be preferred; For the Civil Magiſtrates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubmit to the Spiritual, and might lawfully be reſiſted, and That it was the Duty very Prieſt to give any man Abſolution that ſhould be concerned therein, with ſev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral other Seditious and Traiterous Expreſſions. And further <hi>Mr. Praunce</hi> having ſeveral times fallen into diſcourſe upon ſome occaſions concerning the nature of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Abſolution given by him and other Prieſts, he the ſaid Father <hi>James</hi> did declare That ſuch Abſolution was a full and perfect Remiſſion of Sin, and ſuch an Acquit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is rendred any man as innocent and free from Guilt as the firſt day he was born, fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> any actual Tranſgreſſion. Then he askt him, for Example. If a perſon ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a Sin, and confeſs it to him, or any other Prieſt, and receive an Abſolution, a were afterwards taxed or queſtioned for that Fact, Whether he might with a <hi>ſafe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſcience, and without Sin ſay be was innocent.</hi> To which the ſaid Father <hi>James</hi> repli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> That if ſuch perſon had received ſuch Abſolution, and performed the Penance impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon him, he may lawfully ſay, He was innocent: for, ſays he, When God by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mouth of his Prieſt, has abſolved any perſon, he becomes innocent in the ſight of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and being ſo, has no reaſon to impeach himſelf by owning of the Crime before m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nor caſt a ſcandal on the Church, which to do would be a greater ſin, than to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> matter which he is no ways obliged to confeſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103323:17"/>
Theſe and ſeveral other like Diſcourſes to the ſame purport and effect hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather <hi>James</hi> declared to <hi>Mr. Praunce,</hi> inquiring his Inſtructions for the Direction is Conſcience; whereby may appear, by what meaſures ſuch men ſteer the Soul hoſe that ignorantly commit themſelves to their Conduct; and no wonder it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that ſome perſons gaſp out their laſt Breath with pronouncing a Lie, and per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the utmoſt in denial of thoſe Crimes, which both their own Conſciences and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> world know them to be guilty of, ſince they are before hand hardened into a perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That it is not evil, but rather their Duty in reſpect to the Churches Intereſt ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeremy Jennings,</hi> a Secular Prieſt, lately living at <hi>Mr. Ramſeys</hi> near <hi>Norwich</hi> in <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lk;</hi> a little after <hi>Midſummer</hi> laſt, both at Mrs. <hi>Hells</hi> in <hi>Eagle-Court</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mr. Praunces</hi> own Shop, told him, That we ſhould ſhortly ſee better times, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at he did not doubt, but ſuch Roman Catholick Prieſts as he was, ſhould e're lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alk publickly in Parſons habits. He alſo hath reconciled ſeveral (as he hath acknowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged) to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and amongſt his Acquaintance was very free of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eads, and Prayer books, and hath been heard to ſay Maſs at Sir <hi>Henry Benifields,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Oxford. Hall</hi> in <hi>Norfolk;</hi> So that by ſuch his aforeſaid Words, there is good reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge that the ſaid <hi>Jennings</hi> was acquainted with the Plot, nay it is reaſonable to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e that there was not a Prieſt in <hi>England,</hi> nay ſcarce any Gentleman of Note, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te perſon of any Condition of the Roman Catholick Perſwaſion, but was privy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaid Plot and Conſpiracy, if not as to the particular Intrigues, yet at leaſt as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> General Subſtance and Deſigns thereof.</p>
               <p>There was one Monſieur <hi>L' Hay</hi> (to the beſt of Mr. <hi>Praunces</hi> remembrance, that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s right name) who not much above a year ago retaining to a Foreigner, a Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> condition (whoſe name and Quality is not convenient here to mention) did debauch young Woman, and to avoid Charge that he ſuſpected might enſue, by her proving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith Child, procured a certain perſon of his acquaintance to be married unto her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d after this, privately bargained to commit Adultery with her for ſo much a time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which he practiſed ſo long without payment, that at laſt at the rate agreed on, he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> in her debt, which refuſing or avoiding to pay, the Woman impatient to be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ved, did repair unto his Lords Houſe, and getting acceſs to him complained of his Prieſts owing her Twenty pounds; who demanding for what? She, after ſome tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ings of pretended modeſty, confeſſed it was for the ill uſe of her Body; the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſurprized, and ſcarce believing her, askt her when the laſt time was that he had do with her? She anſwered on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt about Nine of the Clock in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on; the Gentleman remembring that his Prieſt was that day at Maſs; told her, She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s certainly miſtaken; but ſhe perſevering in her ſtory, he called in the Prieſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanding if he owed her any money; which he not being able to deny, nor yet to clare on what good account he became ſo indebted to her, his Maſter could not but include him Guilty, and began to upbraid him, ſaying, Are not you a moſt profane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>llain to lye with this Woman at Nine a clock and approach to the Altar, and offer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceive Gods Body before Ten, and that without any Abſolution too? The Prieſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uld not deny but that he was Rogue enough, but as to the laſt particular, aſſured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m he had Abſolution. And being inquired how or from whom, after ſome Evaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſed that are her <hi>French</hi> Prieſt and he both lay with her ſucceſſively at that
<pb facs="tcp:103323:17"/>time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that they mutually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> each other Abſolution; which is a notable Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> method of Whoring, and as 'tis likely often practiſed by theſe Ghoſtly Fathers. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elation Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> doth not aver upon his own knowledge, but knew the ſaid <hi>Hay</hi> very well, and was moſt credibly informed and aſſured of the Truth there.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="attestation">
            <p>The foregoing Narrative touching the Murther of <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey,</hi> and other Paſſages relating the horrid <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, were written by my Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns, and put into <hi>Method</hi> for the Preſs, the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g dictated by me, and taken all along from my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mouth: And having ſince peruſed it all over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own the ſame, and atteſt the truth of the ſeveral particulars and things therein contained, as they are are related and ſet forth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Miles Prance.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103323:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:103323:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
